<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="usfx_to_xhtml.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">


<bk id="40" name="MATTHEW" short_name="MAT" order="47">
<mbk>40</mbk>

<container id="40.1.0-40.1.0">
<bcv bcv="40.1.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="1"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.1"><v id="1"></v>THE book of the generation of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.2"><v id="2"></v>Abraham begot Isaac. And Isaac begot Jacob. And Jacob begot Judas and his brethren. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.3"><v id="3"></v>And Judas begot Phares and Zara of Thamar. And Phares begot Esron. And Esron begot Aram. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.4"><v id="4"></v>And Aram begot Aminadab. And Aminadab begot Naasson. And Naasson begot Salmon. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.5"><v id="5"></v>And Salmon begot Booz of Rahab. And Booz begot Obed of Ruth. And Obed begot Jesse. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.6"><v id="6"></v>And Jesse begot David the king. And David the king begot Solomon, of her that had been the wife of Urias. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.7"><v id="7"></v>And Solomon begot Roboam. And Roboam begot Abia. And Abia begot Asa. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.8"><v id="8"></v>And Asa begot Josaphat. And Josaphat begot Joram. And Joram begot Ozias. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.9"><v id="9"></v>And Ozias begot Joatham. And Joatham begot Achaz. And Achaz begot Ezechias. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.10"><v id="10"></v>And Ezechias begot Manasses. And Manesses begot Amon. And Amon begot Josias. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.11"><v id="11"></v>And Josias begot Jechonias and his brethren in the transmigration of Babylon. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.12"><v id="12"></v>And after the transmigration of Babylon, Jechonias begot Salathiel. And Salathiel begot Zorobabel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.13"><v id="13"></v>And Zorobabel begot Abiud. And Abiud begot Eliacim. And Eliacim begot Azor. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.14"><v id="14"></v>And Azor begot Sadoc. And Sadoc begot Achim. And Achim begot Eliud. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.15"><v id="15"></v>And Eliud begot Eleazar. And Eleazar begot Mathan. And Mathan begot Jacob. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.16"><v id="16"></v>And Jacob begot Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.17"><v id="17"></v>So all the generations, from Abraham to David, are fourteen generations. And from David to the transmigration of Babylon, are fourteen generations: and from the transmigration of Babylon to Christ are fourteen generations. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.18"><v id="18"></v>Now the generation of Christ was in this wise. When as his mother Mary was espoused to Joseph, before they came together, she was found with child, of the Holy Ghost. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.19"><v id="19"></v>Whereupon Joseph her husband, being a just man, and not willing publicly to expose her, was minded to put her away privately. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.20"><v id="20"></v>But while he thought on these things, behold the angel of the Lord appeared to him in his sleep, saying: Joseph, son of David, fear not to take unto thee Mary thy wife, for that which is conceived in her, is of the Holy Ghost. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.21"><v id="21"></v>And she shall bring forth a son: and thou shalt call his name JESUS. For he shall save his people from their sins. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.22"><v id="22"></v>Now all this was done that it might be fulfilled which the Lord spoke by the prophet, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.23"><v id="23"></v>Behold a virgin shall be with child, and bring forth a son, and they shall call his name Emmanuel, which being interpreted is, God with us. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.24"><v id="24"></v>And Joseph rising up from sleep, did as the angel of the Lord had commanded him, and took unto him his wife. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.1.25"><v id="25"></v>And he knew her not till she brought forth her firstborn son: and he called his name JESUS. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.2.0-40.2.0">
<bcv bcv="40.2.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="2"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.1"><v id="1"></v>WHEN Jesus therefore was born in Bethlehem of Juda, in the days of king Herod, behold, there came wise men from the east to Jerusalem. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.2"><v id="2"></v>Saying, Where is he that is born king of the Jews? For we have seen his star in the east, and are come to adore him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.3"><v id="3"></v>And king Herod hearing this, was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.4"><v id="4"></v>And assembling together all the chief priests and the scribes of the people, he inquired of them where Christ should be born. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.5"><v id="5"></v>But they said to him: In Bethlehem of Juda. For so it is written by the prophet: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.6"><v id="6"></v>And thou Bethlehem the land of Juda art not the least among the princes of Juda: for out of thee shall come forth the captain that shall rule my people Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.7"><v id="7"></v>Then Herod, privately calling the wise men, learned diligently of them the time of the star which appeared to them; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.8"><v id="8"></v>And sending them into Bethlehem, said: Go and diligently inquire after the child, and when you have found him, bring me word again, that I also may come to adore him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.9"><v id="9"></v>Who having heard the king, went their way; and behold the star which they had seen in the east, went before them, until it came and stood over where the child was. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.10"><v id="10"></v>And seeing the star they rejoiced with exceeding great joy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.11"><v id="11"></v>And entering into the house, they found the child with Mary his mother, and falling down they adored him; and opening their treasures, they offered him gifts; gold, frankincense, and myrrh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.12"><v id="12"></v>And having received an answer in sleep that they should not return to Herod, they went back another way into their country. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.13"><v id="13"></v>And after they were departed, behold an angel of the Lord appeared in sleep to Joseph, saying: Arise, and take the child and his mother, and fly into Egypt: and be there until I shall tell thee. For it will come to pass that Herod will seek the child to destroy him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.14"><v id="14"></v>Who arose, and took the child and his mother by night, and retired into Egypt: and he was there until the death of Herod: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.15"><v id="15"></v>That it might be fulfilled which the Lord spoke by the prophet, saying: Out of Egypt have I called my son. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.16"><v id="16"></v>Then Herod perceiving that he was deluded by the wise men, was exceeding angry; and sending killed all the men children that were in Bethlehem, and in all the borders thereof, from two years old and under, according to the time which he had diligently inquired of the wise men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.17"><v id="17"></v>Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremias the prophet, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.18"><v id="18"></v>A voice in Rama was heard, lamentation and great mourning; Rachel bewailing her children, and would not be comforted, because they are not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.19"><v id="19"></v>But when Herod was dead, behold an angel of the Lord appeared in sleep to Joseph in Egypt, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.20"><v id="20"></v>Saying: Arise, and take the child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel. For they are dead that sought the life of the child. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.21"><v id="21"></v>Who arose, and took the child and his mother, and came into the land of Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.22"><v id="22"></v>But hearing that Archelaus reigned in Judea in the room of Herod his father, he was afraid to go thither: and being warned in sleep retired into the quarters of Galilee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.2.23"><v id="23"></v>And coming he dwelt in a city called Nazareth: that it might be fulfilled which was said by prophets: That he shall be called a Nazarene. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.3.0-40.3.0">
<bcv bcv="40.3.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="3"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.1"><v id="1"></v>AND in those days cometh John the Baptist preaching in the desert of Judea. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.2"><v id="2"></v>And saying: Do penance: for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.3"><v id="3"></v>For this is he that was spoken of by Isaias the prophet, saying: A voice of one crying in the desert, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make straight his paths. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.4"><v id="4"></v>And the same John had his garment of camels' hair, and a leathern girdle about his loins: and his meat was locusts and wild honey. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.5"><v id="5"></v>Then went out to him Jerusalem and all Judea, and all the country about Jordan: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.6"><v id="6"></v>And were baptized by him in the Jordan, confessing their sins. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.7"><v id="7"></v>And seeing many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said to them: Ye brood of vipers, who hath shewed you to flee from the wrath to come? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.8"><v id="8"></v>Bring forth therefore fruit worthy of penance. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.9"><v id="9"></v>And think not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham for our father. For I tell you that God is able of these stones to raise up children to Abraham. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.10"><v id="10"></v>For now the axe is laid to the root of the trees. Every tree therefore that doth not yield good fruit, shall be cut down, and cast into the fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.11"><v id="11"></v>I indeed baptize you in the water unto penance, but he that shall come after me, is mightier than I, whose shoes I am not worthy to bear; he shall baptize you in the Holy Ghost and fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.12"><v id="12"></v>Whose fan is in his hand, and he will thoroughly cleanse his floor and gather his wheat into the barn; but the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.13"><v id="13"></v>Then cometh Jesus from Galilee to the Jordan, unto John, to be baptized by him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.14"><v id="14"></v>But John stayed him, saying: I ought to be baptized by thee, and comest thou to me? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.15"><v id="15"></v>And Jesus answering, said to him: Suffer it to be so now. For so it becometh us to fulfill all justice. Then he suffered him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.16"><v id="16"></v>And Jesus being baptized, forthwith came out of the water: and lo, the heavens were opened to him: and he saw the Spirit of God descending as a dove, and coming upon him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.3.17"><v id="17"></v>And behold a voice from heaven, saying: This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.4.0-40.4.0">
<bcv bcv="40.4.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="4"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.1"><v id="1"></v>THEN Jesus was led by the spirit into the desert, to be tempted by the devil. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.2"><v id="2"></v>And when he had fasted forty days and forty nights, afterwards he was hungry. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.3"><v id="3"></v>And the tempter coming said to him: If thou be the Son of God, command that these stones be made bread. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.4"><v id="4"></v>Who answered and said: It is written, Not in bread alone doth man live, but in every word that proceedeth from the mouth of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.5"><v id="5"></v>Then the devil took him up into the holy city, and set him upon the pinnacle of the temple, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.6"><v id="6"></v>And said to him: If thou be the Son of God, cast thyself down, for it is written: That he hath given his angels charge over thee, and in their hands shall they bear thee up, lest perhaps thou dash thy foot against a stone. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.7"><v id="7"></v>Jesus said to him: It is written again: Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.8"><v id="8"></v>Again the devil took him up into a very high mountain, and shewed him all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.9"><v id="9"></v>And said to him: All these will I give thee, if falling down thou wilt adore me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.10"><v id="10"></v>Then Jesus saith to him: Begone, Satan: for it is written, The Lord thy God shalt thou adore, and him only shalt thou serve. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.11"><v id="11"></v>Then the devil left him; and behold angels came and ministered to him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.12"><v id="12"></v>And when Jesus had heard that John was delivered up, he retired into Galilee: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.13"><v id="13"></v>And leaving the city Nazareth, he came and dwelt in Capharnaum on the sea coast, in the borders of Zabulon and Nephthalim; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.14"><v id="14"></v>That it might be fulfilled which was said by Isaias the prophet: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.15"><v id="15"></v>Land of Zabulon and land of Nephthalim, the way of the sea beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.16"><v id="16"></v>The people that sat in darkness, hath seen great light: and to them that sat in the region of the shadow of death, light is sprung up. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.17"><v id="17"></v>From that time Jesus began to preach, and to say: Do penance, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.18"><v id="18"></v>And Jesus walking by the sea of Galilee, saw two brethren, Simon who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea (for they were fishers). </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.19"><v id="19"></v>And he saith to them: Come ye after me, and I will make you to be fishers of men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.20"><v id="20"></v>And they immediately leaving their nets, followed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.21"><v id="21"></v>And going on from thence, he saw other two brethren, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in a ship with Zebedee their father, mending their nets: and he called them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.22"><v id="22"></v>And they forthwith left their nets and father, and followed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.23"><v id="23"></v>And Jesus went about all Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom: and healing all manner of sickness and every infirmity, among the people. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.24"><v id="24"></v>And his fame went throughout all Syria, and they presented to him all sick people that were taken with divers diseases and torments, and such as were possessed by devils, and lunatics, and those that had palsy, and he cured them: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.4.25"><v id="25"></v>And much people followed him from Galilee, and from Decapolis, and from Jerusalem, and from Judea, and from beyond the Jordan. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.5.0-40.5.0">
<bcv bcv="40.5.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="5"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.1"><v id="1"></v>AND seeing the multitudes, he went up into a mountain, and when he was set down, his disciples came unto him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.2"><v id="2"></v>And opening his mouth, he taught them, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.3"><v id="3"></v>Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.4"><v id="4"></v>Blessed are the meek: for they shall possess the land. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.5"><v id="5"></v>Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.6"><v id="6"></v>Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after justice: for they shall have their fill. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.7"><v id="7"></v>Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.8"><v id="8"></v>Blessed are the clean of heart: for they shall see God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.9"><v id="9"></v>Blesses are the peacemakers: for they shall be called children of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.10"><v id="10"></v>Blessed are they that suffer persecution for justice' sake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.11"><v id="11"></v>Blessed are ye when they shall revile you, and persecute you, and speak all that is evil against you, untruly, for my sake: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.12"><v id="12"></v>Be glad and rejoice, for your reward is very great in heaven. For so they persecuted the prophets that were before you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.13"><v id="13"></v>You are the salt of the earth. But if the salt lose its savour, wherewith shall it be salted? It is good for nothing any more but to be cast out, and to be trodden on by men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.14"><v id="14"></v>You are the light of the world. A city seated on a mountain cannot be hid. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.15"><v id="15"></v>Neither do men light a candle and put it under a bushel, but upon a candlestick, that it may shine to all that are in the house. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.16"><v id="16"></v>So let your light shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.17"><v id="17"></v>Do not think that I am come to destroy the law, or the prophets. I am not come to destroy, but to fulfill. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.18"><v id="18"></v>For amen I say unto you, till heaven and earth pass, one jot, or one tittle shall not pass of the law, till all be fulfilled. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.19"><v id="19"></v>He therefore that shall break one of these least commandments, and shall so teach men, shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven. But he that shall do and teach, he shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.20"><v id="20"></v>For I tell you, that unless your justice abound more than that of the scribes and Pharisees, you shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.21"><v id="21"></v>You have heard that it was said to them of old: Thou shalt not kill. And whosoever shall kill shall be in danger of the judgment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.22"><v id="22"></v>But I say to you, that whosoever is angry with his brother, shall be in danger of the judgment. And whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca, shall be in danger of the council. And whosoever shall say, Thou Fool, shall be in danger of hell fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.23"><v id="23"></v>If therefore thou offer thy gift at the altar, and there thou remember that thy brother hath any thing against thee; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.24"><v id="24"></v>Leave there thy offering before the altar, and go first to be reconciled to thy brother: and then coming thou shalt offer thy gift. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.25"><v id="25"></v>Be at agreement with thy adversary betimes, whilst thou art in the way with him: lest perhaps the adversary deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and thou be cast into prison. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.26"><v id="26"></v>Amen I say to thee, thou shalt not go out from thence till thou repay the last farthing. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.27"><v id="27"></v>You have heard that it was said to them of old: Thou shalt not commit adultery. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.28"><v id="28"></v>But I say to you, that whosoever shall look on a woman to lust after her, hath already committed adultery with her in his heart. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.29"><v id="29"></v>And if thy right eye scandalize thee, pluck it out and cast it from thee. For it is expedient for thee that one of thy members should perish, rather than that thy whole body be cast into hell. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.30"><v id="30"></v>And if thy right hand scandalize thee, cut it off, and cast it from thee: for it is expedient for thee that one of thy members should perish, rather than that thy whole body be cast into hell. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.31"><v id="31"></v>And it hath been said, Whoseoever shall put away his wife, let him give her a bill of divorce. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.32"><v id="32"></v>But I say to you, that whosoever shall put away his wife, excepting for the cause of fornication, maketh her to commit adultery: and he that shall marry her that is put away, committeth adultery. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.33"><v id="33"></v>Again you have heard that it was said to them of old, Thou shalt not forswear thyself: but thou shalt perform thy oaths to the Lord. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.34"><v id="34"></v>But I say to you not to swear at all, neither by heaven, for it is the throne of God: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.35"><v id="35"></v>Nor by the earth, for it is his footstool: nor by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great king: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.36"><v id="36"></v>Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, because thou canst not make one hair white or black. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.37"><v id="37"></v>But let your speech be yea, yea: no, no: and that which is over and above these, is of evil. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.38"><v id="38"></v>You have heard that it hath been said, An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.39"><v id="39"></v>But I say to you not to resist evil: but if one strike thee on thy right cheek, turn to him also the other: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.40"><v id="40"></v>And if a man will contend with thee in judgment, and take away thy coat, let go thy cloak also unto him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.41"><v id="41"></v>And whosoever will force thee one mile, go with him other two, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.42"><v id="42"></v>Give to him that asketh of thee and from him that would borrow of thee turn not away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.43"><v id="43"></v>You have heard that it hath been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbor, and hate thy enemy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.44"><v id="44"></v>But I say to you, Love your enemies: do good to them that hate you: and pray for them that persecute and calumniate you: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.45"><v id="45"></v>That you may be the children of your Father who is in heaven, who maketh his sun to rise upon the good, and bad, and raineth upon the just and the unjust. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.46"><v id="46"></v>For if you love them that love you, what reward shall you have? do not even the publicans this? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.47"><v id="47"></v>And if you salute your brethren only, what do you more? do not also the heathens this? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.5.48"><v id="48"></v>Be you therefore perfect, as also your heavenly Father is perfect. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.6.0-40.6.0">
<bcv bcv="40.6.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="6"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.1"><v id="1"></v>TAKE heed that you do not your justice before men, to be seen by them: otherwise you shall not have a reward of your Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.2"><v id="2"></v>Therefore when thou dost an almsdeed, sound not a trumpet before thee, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, that they may be honoured by men. Amen I say to you, they have received their reward. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.3"><v id="3"></v>But when thou dost alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.4"><v id="4"></v>That thy alms may be in secret, and thy Father who seeth in secret will repay thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.5"><v id="5"></v>And when ye pray, you shall not be as the hypocrites, that love to stand and pray in the synagogues and corners of the streets, that they may be seen by men: Amen I say to you, they have received their reward. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.6"><v id="6"></v>But thou when thou shalt pray, enter into thy chamber, and having shut the door, pray to thy Father in secret: and thy Father who seeth in secret will repay thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.7"><v id="7"></v>And when you are praying, speak not much, as the heathens. For they think that in their much speaking they may be heard. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.8"><v id="8"></v>Be not you therefore like to them, for your Father knoweth what is needful for you, before you ask him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.9"><v id="9"></v>Thus therefore shall you pray: Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.10"><v id="10"></v>Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.11"><v id="11"></v>Give us this day our supersubstantial bread. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.12"><v id="12"></v>And forgive us our debts, as we also forgive our debtors. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.13"><v id="13"></v>And lead us not into temptation. But deliver us from evil. Amen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.14"><v id="14"></v>For if you will forgive men their offences, your heavenly Father will forgive you also your offences. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.15"><v id="15"></v>But if you will not forgive men, neither will your Father forgive you your offences. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.16"><v id="16"></v>And when you fast, be not as the hypocrites, sad. For they disfigure their faces, that they may appear unto men to fast. Amen I say to you, they have received their reward. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.17"><v id="17"></v>But thou, when thou fastest anoint thy head, and wash thy face; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.18"><v id="18"></v>That thou appear not to men to fast, but to thy Father who is in secret: and thy Father who seeth in secret, will repay thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.19"><v id="19"></v>Lay not up to yourselves treasures on earth: where the rust, and moth consume, and where thieves break through and steal. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.20"><v id="20"></v>But lay up to yourselves treasures in heaven: where neither the rust nor moth doth consume, and where thieves do not break through, nor steal. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.21"><v id="21"></v>For where thy treasure is, there is thy heart also. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.22"><v id="22"></v>The light of thy body is thy eye. If thy eye be single, thy whole body shall be lightsome. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.23"><v id="23"></v>But if thy eye be evil thy whole body shall be darksome. If then the light that is in thee, be darkness: the darkness itself how great shall it be! </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.24"><v id="24"></v>No man can serve two masters. For either he will hate the one, and love the other: or he will sustain the one, and despise the other. You cannot serve God and mammon. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.25"><v id="25"></v>Therefore I say to you, be not solicitous for your life, what you shall eat, nor for your body, what you shall put on. Is not the life more than the meat: and the body more than the raiment? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.26"><v id="26"></v>Behold the birds of the air, for they neither sow, nor do they reap, nor gather into barns: and your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are not you of much more value than they? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.27"><v id="27"></v>And which of you by taking thought, can add to his stature by one cubit? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.28"><v id="28"></v>And for raiment why are you solicitous? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow: they labour not, neither do they spin. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.29"><v id="29"></v>But I say to you, that not even Solomon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.30"><v id="30"></v>And if the grass of the field, which is to day, and to morrow is cast into the oven, God doth so clothe: how much more you, O ye of little faith? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.31"><v id="31"></v>Be not solicitous therefore, saying, What shall we eat: or what shall we drink, or wherewith shall we be clothed? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.32"><v id="32"></v>For after all these things do the heathens seek. For your Father knoweth that you have need of all these things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.33"><v id="33"></v>Seek ye therefore first the kingdom of God, and his justice, and all these things shall be added unto you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.6.34"><v id="34"></v>Be not therefore solicitous for to morrow; for the morrow will be solicitous for itself. Sufficient for the day is the evil thereof. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.7.0-40.7.0">
<bcv bcv="40.7.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="7"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.1"><v id="1"></v>JUDGE not, that you may not be judged, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.2"><v id="2"></v>For with what judgment you judge, you shall be judged: and with what measure you mete, it shall be measured to you again. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.3"><v id="3"></v>Any why seest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye; and seest not the beam that is in thy own eye? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.4"><v id="4"></v>Or how sayest thou to thy brother: Let me cast the mote out of thy eye; and behold a beam is in thy own eye? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.5"><v id="5"></v>Thou hypocrite, cast out first the beam in thy own eye, and then shalt thou see to cast out the mote out of thy brother's eye. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.6"><v id="6"></v>Give not that which is holy to dogs; neither cast ye your pearls before swine, lest perhaps they trample them under their feet, and turning upon you, they tear you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.7"><v id="7"></v>Ask, and it shall be given you: seek, and you shall find: knock, and it shall be opened to you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.8"><v id="8"></v>For every one that asketh, receiveth: and he that seeketh, findeth: and to him that knocketh, it shall be opened. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.9"><v id="9"></v>Or what man is there among you, of whom if his son shall ask bread, will he reach him a stone? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.10"><v id="10"></v>Or if he shall ask him a fish, will he reach him a serpent? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.11"><v id="11"></v>If you then being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children: how much more will your Father who is in heaven, give good things to them that ask him? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.12"><v id="12"></v>All things therefore whatsoever you would that men should do to you, do you also to them. For this is the law and the prophets. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.13"><v id="13"></v>Enter ye in at the narrow gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to destruction, and many there are who go in thereat. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.14"><v id="14"></v>How narrow is the gate, and strait is the way that leadeth to life: and few there are that find it! </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.15"><v id="15"></v>Beware of false prophets, who come to you in the clothing of sheep, but inwardly they are ravening wolves. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.16"><v id="16"></v>By their fruits you shall know them. Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.17"><v id="17"></v>Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit, and the evil tree bringeth forth evil fruit. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.18"><v id="18"></v>A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can an evil tree bring forth good fruit. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.19"><v id="19"></v>Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, shall be cut down, and shall be cast into the fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.20"><v id="20"></v>Wherefore by their fruits you shall know them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.21"><v id="21"></v>Not every one that saith to me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven: but he that doth the will of my Father who is in heaven, he shall enter into the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.22"><v id="22"></v>Many will say to me in that day: Lord, Lord, have not we prophesied in thy name, and cast out devils in thy name, and done many miracles in thy name? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.23"><v id="23"></v>And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you: depart from me, you that work iniquity. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.24"><v id="24"></v>Every one therefore that heareth these my words, and doth them, shall be likened to a wise man that built his house upon a rock, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.25"><v id="25"></v>And the rain fell, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and they beat upon that house, and it fell not, for it was founded on a rock. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.26"><v id="26"></v>And every one that heareth these my words, and doth them not, shall be like a foolish man that built his house upon the sand, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.27"><v id="27"></v>And the rain fell, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and they beat upon that house, and it fell, and great was the fall thereof. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.28"><v id="28"></v>And it came to pass when Jesus had fully ended these words, the people were in admiration at his doctrine. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.7.29"><v id="29"></v>For he was teaching them as one having power, and not as the scribes and Pharisees. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.8.0-40.8.0">
<bcv bcv="40.8.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="8"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.1"><v id="1"></v>AND when he was come down from the mountain, great multitudes followed him: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.2"><v id="2"></v>And behold a leper came and adored him, saying: Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.3"><v id="3"></v>And Jesus stretching forth his hand, touched him, saying: I will, be thou made clean. And forthwith his leprosy was cleansed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.4"><v id="4"></v>And Jesus saith to him: See thou tell no man: but go, shew thyself to the priest, and offer the gift which Moses commanded for a testimony unto them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.5"><v id="5"></v>And when he had entered into Capharnaum, there came to him a centurion, beseeching him, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.6"><v id="6"></v>And saying, Lord, my servant lieth at home sick of the palsy, and is grieviously tormented. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.7"><v id="7"></v>And Jesus saith to him: I will come and heal him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.8"><v id="8"></v>And the centurion making answer, said: Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldst enter under my roof: but only say the word, and my servant shall be healed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.9"><v id="9"></v>For I also am a man subject to authority, having under me soldiers; and I say to this, Go, and he goeth, and to another, Come, and he cometh, and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.10"><v id="10"></v>And Jesus hearing this, marvelled; and said to them that followed him: Amen I say to you, I have not found so great faith in Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.11"><v id="11"></v>And I say to you that many shall come from the east and the west, and shall sit down with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.12"><v id="12"></v>But the children of the kingdom shall be cast out into the exterior darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.13"><v id="13"></v>And Jesus said to the centurion: Go, and as thou hast believed, so be it done to thee. And the servant was healed at the same hour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.14"><v id="14"></v>And when Jesus was come into Peter's house, he saw his wife's mother lying, and sick of a fever: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.15"><v id="15"></v>And he touched her hand, and the fever left her, and she arose and ministered to them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.16"><v id="16"></v>And when evening was come, they brought to him many that were possessed with devils: and he cast out the spirits with his word: and all that were sick he healed: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.17"><v id="17"></v>That it might be fulfilled, which was spoken by the prophet Isaias, saying: He took our infirmities, and bore our diseases. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.18"><v id="18"></v>And Jesus seeing great multitudes about him, gave orders to pass over the water. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.19"><v id="19"></v>And a certain scribe came and said to him: Master, I will follow thee whithersoever thou shalt go. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.20"><v id="20"></v>And Jesus saith to him: The foxes have holes, and the birds of the air nests: but the son of man hath not where to lay his head. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.21"><v id="21"></v>And another of his disciples said to him: Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.22"><v id="22"></v>But Jesus said to him: Follow me, and let the dead bury their dead. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.23"><v id="23"></v>And when he entered into the boat, his disciples followed him: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.24"><v id="24"></v>And behold a great tempest arose in the sea, so that the boat was covered with waves, but he was asleep. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.25"><v id="25"></v>And they came to him, and awaked him, saying: Lord, save us, we perish. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.26"><v id="26"></v>And Jesus saith to them: Why are you fearful, O ye of little faith? Then rising up he commanded the winds, and the sea, and there came a great calm. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.27"><v id="27"></v>But the men wondered, saying: What manner of man is this, for the winds and the sea obey him? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.28"><v id="28"></v>And when he was come on the other side of the water, into the country of the Gerasens, there met him two that were possessed with devils, coming out of the sepulchres, exceeding fierce, so that none could pass by that way. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.29"><v id="29"></v>And behold they cried out, saying: What have we to do with thee, Jesus Son of God? art thou come hither to torment us before the time? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.30"><v id="30"></v>And there was, not far from them, an herd of many swine feeding. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.31"><v id="31"></v>And the devils besought him, saying: If thou cast us out hence, send us into the herd of swine. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.32"><v id="32"></v>And he said to them: Go. But they going out went into the swine, and behold the whole herd ran violently down a steep place into the sea: and they perished in the waters. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.33"><v id="33"></v>And they that kept them fled: and coming into the city, told every thing, and concerning them that had been possessed by the devils. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.8.34"><v id="34"></v>And behold the whole city went out to meet Jesus, and when they saw him, they besought him that he would depart from their coasts. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.9.0-40.9.0">
<bcv bcv="40.9.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="9"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.1"><v id="1"></v>AND entering into a boat, he passed over the water and came into his own city. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.2"><v id="2"></v>And behold they brought to him one sick of the palsy lying in a bed. And Jesus, seeing their faith, said to the man sick of the palsy: Be of good heart, son, thy sins are forgiven thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.3"><v id="3"></v>And behold some of the scribes said within themselves: He blasphemeth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.4"><v id="4"></v>And Jesus seeing their thoughts, said: Why do you think evil in your hearts? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.5"><v id="5"></v>Whether is easier, to say, Thy sins are forgiven thee: or to say, Arise, and walk? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.6"><v id="6"></v>But that you may know that the Son of man hath power on earth to forgive sins, (then said he to the man sick of palsy,) Arise, take up thy bed, and go into thy house. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.7"><v id="7"></v>And he arose, and went into his house. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.8"><v id="8"></v>And the multitude seeing it, feared, and glorified God that gave such power to men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.9"><v id="9"></v>And when Jesus passed on from hence, he saw a man sitting in the custom house, named Matthew; and he saith to him: Follow me. And he rose up and followed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.10"><v id="10"></v>And it came to pass as he was sitting at meat in the house, behold many publicans and sinners came, and sat down with Jesus and his disciples. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.11"><v id="11"></v>And the Pharisees seeing it, said to his disciples: Why doth your master eat with publicans and sinners? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.12"><v id="12"></v>But Jesus hearing it, said: They that are in health need not a physician, but they that are ill. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.13"><v id="13"></v>Go then and learn what this meaneth, I will have mercy and not sacrifice. For I am not come to call the just, but sinners. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.14"><v id="14"></v>Then came to him the disciples of John, saying: Why do we and the Pharisees fast often, but thy disciples do not fast? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.15"><v id="15"></v>And Jesus said to them: Can the children of the bridegroom mourn, as long as the bridegroom is with them? But the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them, and then they shall fast. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.16"><v id="16"></v>And nobody putteth a piece of raw cloth unto an old garment. For it taketh away the fullness thereof from the garment, and there is made a greater rent. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.17"><v id="17"></v>Neither do they put new wine into old bottles. Otherwise the bottles break, and the wine runneth out, and the bottles perish. But new wine they put into new bottles: and both are preserved. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.18"><v id="18"></v>As he was speaking these things unto them, behold a certain ruler came up, and adored him, saying: Lord, my daughter is even now dead; but come, lay thy hand upon her, and she shall live. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.19"><v id="19"></v>And Jesus rising up followed him, with his disciples. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.20"><v id="20"></v>And behold a woman who was troubled with an issue of blood twelve years, came behind him, and touched the hem of his garment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.21"><v id="21"></v>For she said within herself: If I shall touch only his garment, I shall be healed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.22"><v id="22"></v>But Jesus turning and seeing her, said: Be of good heart, daughter, thy faith hath made thee whole. And the woman was made whole from that hour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.23"><v id="23"></v>And when Jesus was come into the house of the ruler, and saw the minstrels and the multitude making a rout, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.24"><v id="24"></v>He said: Give place, for the girl is not dead, but sleepeth. And they laughed him to scorn. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.25"><v id="25"></v>And when the multitude was put forth, he went in, and took her by the hand. And the maid arose. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.26"><v id="26"></v>And the fame hereof went abroad into all that country. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.27"><v id="27"></v>And as Jesus passed from thence, there followed him two blind men crying out and saying, Have mercy on us, O Son of David. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.28"><v id="28"></v>And when he was come to the house, the blind men came to him. And Jesus saith to them, Do you believe, that I can do this unto you? They say to him, Yea, Lord. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.29"><v id="29"></v>Then he touched their eyes, saying, According to your faith, be it done unto you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.30"><v id="30"></v>And their eyes were opened, and Jesus strictly charged them, saying, See that no man know this. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.31"><v id="31"></v>But they going out, spread his fame abroad in all that country. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.32"><v id="32"></v>And when they were gone out, behold they brought him a dumb man, possessed with a devil. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.33"><v id="33"></v>And after the devil was cast out, the dumb man spoke, and the multitudes wondered, saying, Never was the like seen in Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.34"><v id="34"></v>But the Pharisees said, By the prince of devils he casteth out devils. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.35"><v id="35"></v>And Jesus went about all the cities, and towns, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing every disease, and every infirmity. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.36"><v id="36"></v>And seeing the multitudes, he had compassion on them: because they were distressed, and lying like sheep that have no shepherd. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.37"><v id="37"></v>Then he saith to his disciples, The harvest indeed is great, but the labourers are few. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.9.38"><v id="38"></v>Pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he send forth labourers into his harvest. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.10.0-40.10.0">
<bcv bcv="40.10.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="10"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.1"><v id="1"></v>AND having called his twelve disciples together, he gave them power over unclean spirits, to cast them out, and to heal all manner of diseases, and all manner of infirmities. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.2"><v id="2"></v>And the names of the twelve apostles are these: The first, Simon who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.3"><v id="3"></v>James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, Philip and Bartholomew, Thomas and Matthew the publican, and James the son of Alpheus, and Thaddeus, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.4"><v id="4"></v>Simon the Cananean, and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.5"><v id="5"></v>These twelve Jesus sent: commanding them, saying: Go ye not into the way of the Gentiles, and into the city of the Samaritans enter ye not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.6"><v id="6"></v>But go ye rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.7"><v id="7"></v>And going, preach, saying: The kingdom of heaven is at hand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.8"><v id="8"></v>Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse the lepers, cast out devils: freely have you received, freely give. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.9"><v id="9"></v>Do not possess gold, nor silver, nor money in your purses: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.10"><v id="10"></v>Nor scrip for your journey, nor two coats, nor shoes, nor a staff; for the workman is worthy of his meat. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.11"><v id="11"></v>And into whatsoever city or town you shall enter, inquire who in it is worthy, and there abide till you go thence. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.12"><v id="12"></v>And when you come into the house, salute it, saying: Peace be to this house. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.13"><v id="13"></v>And if that house be worthy, your peace shall come upon it; but if it be not worthy, your peace shall return to you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.14"><v id="14"></v>And whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words: going forth out of that house or city shake off the dust from your feet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.15"><v id="15"></v>Amen I say to you, it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrha in the day of judgment, than for that city. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.16"><v id="16"></v>Behold I send you as sheep in the midst of wolves. Be ye therefore wise as serpents and simple as doves. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.17"><v id="17"></v>But beware of men. For they will deliver you up in councils, and they will scourge you in their synagogues. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.18"><v id="18"></v>And you shall be brought before governors, and before kings for my sake, for a testimony to them and to the Gentiles: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.19"><v id="19"></v>But when they shall deliver you up, take no thought how or what to speak: for it shall be given you in that hour what to speak. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.20"><v id="20"></v>For it is not you that speak, but the Spirit of your Father that speaketh in you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.21"><v id="21"></v>The brother also shall deliver up the brother to death, and the father the son: and the children shall rise up against their parents, and shall put them to death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.22"><v id="22"></v>And you shall be hated by all men for my name's sake: but he that shall persevere unto the end, he shall be saved. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.23"><v id="23"></v>And when they shall persecute you in this city, flee into another. Amen I say to you, you shall not finish all the cities of Israel, till the Son of man come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.24"><v id="24"></v>The disciple is not above the master, nor the servant above his lord. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.25"><v id="25"></v>It is enough for the disciple that he be as his master, and the servant as his lord. If they have called the goodman of the house Beelzebub, how much more them of his household? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.26"><v id="26"></v>Therefore fear them not. For nothing is covered that shall not be revealed: nor hid, that shall not be known. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.27"><v id="27"></v>That which I tell you in the dark, speak ye in the light: and that which you hear in the ear, preach ye upon the housetops. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.28"><v id="28"></v>And fear ye not them that kill the body, and are not able to kill the soul: but rather fear him that can destroy both soul and body in hell. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.29"><v id="29"></v>Are not two sparrows sold for a farthing? and not one of them shall fall on the ground without your Father. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.30"><v id="30"></v>But the very hairs of your head are all numbered. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.31"><v id="31"></v>Fear not therefore: better are you than many sparrows. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.32"><v id="32"></v>Every one therefore that shall confess me before men, I will also confess him before my Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.33"><v id="33"></v>But he that shall deny me before men, I will also deny him before my Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.34"><v id="34"></v>Do not think that I came to send peace upon earth: I came not to send peace, but the sword. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.35"><v id="35"></v>For I came to set a man at variance against his father, and the daughter against her mother, and the daughter in law against her mother in law. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.36"><v id="36"></v>And as a man's enemies shall be they of his own household. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.37"><v id="37"></v>He that loveth father or mother more than me, is not worthy of me; and he that loveth son or daughter more than me, is not worthy of me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.38"><v id="38"></v>And he that taketh not up his cross, and followeth me, is not worthy of me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.39"><v id="39"></v>He that findeth his life, shall lose it: and he that shall lose his life for me, shall find it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.40"><v id="40"></v>He that receiveth you, receiveth me: and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that sent me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.41"><v id="41"></v>He that receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall receive the reward of a prophet: and he that receiveth a just man in the name of a just man, shall receive the reward of a just man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.10.42"><v id="42"></v>And whosoever shall give to drink to one of these little ones a cup of cold water only in the name of a disciple, amen I say to you, he shall not lose his reward. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.11.0-40.11.0">
<bcv bcv="40.11.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="11"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.1"><v id="1"></v>AND it came to pass, when Jesus had made an end of commanding his twelve disciples, he passed from thence, to teach and preach in their cities. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.2"><v id="2"></v>Now when John had heard in prison the works of Christ: sending two of his disciples he said to him: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.3"><v id="3"></v>Art thou he that art to come, or look we for another? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.4"><v id="4"></v>And Jesus making answer said to them: Go and relate to John what you have heard and seen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.5"><v id="5"></v>The blind see, the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear, the dead rise again, the poor have the gospel preached to them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.6"><v id="6"></v>And blessed is he that shall not be scandalized in me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.7"><v id="7"></v>And when they went their way, Jesus began to say to the multitudes concerning John: What went you out into the desert to see? a reed shaken with the wind? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.8"><v id="8"></v>But what went you out to see? a man clothed in soft garments? Behold they that are clothed in soft garments, are in the houses of kings. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.9"><v id="9"></v>But what went you out to see? a prophet? yea I tell you, and more than a prophet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.10"><v id="10"></v>For this is he of whom it is written: Behold I send my angel before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.11"><v id="11"></v>Amen I say to you, there hath not risen among them that are born of women a greater than John the Baptist: yet he that is the lesser in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.12"><v id="12"></v>And from the days of John the Baptist until now, the kingdom of heaven suffereth violence, and the violent bear it away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.13"><v id="13"></v>For all the prophets and the law prophesied until John: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.14"><v id="14"></v>And if you will receive it, he is Elias that is to come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.15"><v id="15"></v>He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.16"><v id="16"></v>But whereunto shall I esteem this generation to be like? It is like to children sitting in the market place. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.17"><v id="17"></v>Who crying to their companions say: We have piped to you, and you have not danced: we have lamented, and you have not mourned. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.18"><v id="18"></v>For John came neither eating nor drinking; and they say: He hath a devil. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.19"><v id="19"></v>The Son of man came eating and drinking, and they say: Behold a man that is a glutton and a wine drinker, a friend of publicans and sinners. And wisdom is justified by her children. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.20"><v id="20"></v>Then began he to upbraid the cities wherein were done the most of his miracles, for that they had not done penance. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.21"><v id="21"></v>Woe to thee, Corozain, woe to thee, Bethsaida: for if in Tyre and Sidon had been wrought the miracles that have been wrought in you, they had long ago done penance in sackcloth and ashes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.22"><v id="22"></v>But I say unto you, it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in the day of judgment, than for you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.23"><v id="23"></v>And thou Capharnaum, shalt thou be exalted up to heaven? thou shalt go down even unto hell. For if in Sodom had been wrought the miracles that have been wrought in thee, perhaps it had remained unto this day. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.24"><v id="24"></v>But I say unto you, that it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom in the day of judgment, than for thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.25"><v id="25"></v>At that time Jesus answered and said: I confess to thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them to the little ones. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.26"><v id="26"></v>Yea, Father; for so hath it seemed good in thy sight. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.27"><v id="27"></v>All things are delivered to me by my Father. And no one knoweth the Son, but the Father: neither doth any one know the Father, but the Son, and he to whom it shall please the Son to reveal him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.28"><v id="28"></v>Come to me, all you that labour, and are burdened, and I will refresh you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.29"><v id="29"></v>Take up my yoke upon you, and learn of me, because I am meek, and humble of heart: and you shall find rest to your souls. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.11.30"><v id="30"></v>For my yoke is sweet and my burden light. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.12.0-40.12.0">
<bcv bcv="40.12.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="12"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.1"><v id="1"></v>AT that time Jesus went through the corn on the sabbath: and his disciples being hungry, began to pluck the ears, and to eat. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.2"><v id="2"></v>And the Pharisees seeing them, said to him: Behold thy disciples do that which is not lawful to do on the sabbath days. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.3"><v id="3"></v>But he said to them: Have you not read what David did when he was hungry, and they that were with him: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.4"><v id="4"></v>How he entered into the house of God, and did eat the loaves of proposition, which it was not lawful for him to eat, nor for them that were with him, but for the priests only? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.5"><v id="5"></v>Or have ye not read in the law, that on the sabbath days the priests in the temple break the sabbath, and are without blame? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.6"><v id="6"></v>But I tell you that there is here a greater than the temple. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.7"><v id="7"></v>And if you knew what this meaneth: I will have mercy, and not sacrifice: you would never have condemned the innocent. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.8"><v id="8"></v>For the Son of man is Lord even of the sabbath. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.9"><v id="9"></v>And when he has passed from thence, he came into their synagogues. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.10"><v id="10"></v>And behold there was a man who had a withered hand, and they asked him, saying: Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath days? that they might accuse him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.11"><v id="11"></v>But he said to them: What man shall there be among you, that hath one sheep: and if the same fall into a pit on the sabbath day, will he not take hold on it and lift it up? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.12"><v id="12"></v>How much better is a man than a sheep? Therefore it it lawful to do a good deed on the sabbath days. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.13"><v id="13"></v>Then he saith to the man: Stretch forth thy hand; and he stretched it forth, and it was restored to health even as the other. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.14"><v id="14"></v>And the Pharisees going out made a consultation against him, how they might destroy him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.15"><v id="15"></v>But Jesus knowing it, retired from thence: and many followed him, and he healed them all. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.16"><v id="16"></v>And he charged them that they should not make him known. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.17"><v id="17"></v>That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Isaias the prophet, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.18"><v id="18"></v>Behold my servant whom I have chosen, my beloved in whom my soul hath been well pleased. I will put my spirit upon him, and he shall shew judgment to the Gentiles. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.19"><v id="19"></v>He shall not contend, nor cry out, neither shall any man hear his voice in the streets. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.20"><v id="20"></v>The bruised reed he shall not break: and smoking flax he shall not extinguish: till he send forth judgment unto victory. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.21"><v id="21"></v>And in his name the Gentiles shall hope. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.22"><v id="22"></v>Then was offered to him one possessed with a devil, blind and dumb: and he healed him, so that he spoke and saw. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.23"><v id="23"></v>And all the multitudes were amazed, and said: Is not this the son of David? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.24"><v id="24"></v>But the Pharisees hearing it, said: This man casteth not out the devils but by Beelzebub the prince of the devils. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.25"><v id="25"></v>And Jesus knowing their thoughts, said to them: Every kingdom divided against itself shall be made desolate: and every city or house divided against itself shall not stand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.26"><v id="26"></v>And if Satan cast out Satan, he is divided against himself: how then shall his kingdom stand? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.27"><v id="27"></v>And if I by Beelzebub cast out devils, by whom do your children cast them out? Therefore they shall be your judges. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.28"><v id="28"></v>But if I by the Spirit of God cast out devils, then is the kingdom of God come upon you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.29"><v id="29"></v>Or how can any one enter into the house of the strong, and rifle his goods, unless he first bind the strong? and then he will rifle his house. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.30"><v id="30"></v>He that is not with me, is against me: and he that gathereth not with me, scattereth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.31"><v id="31"></v>Therefore I say to you: Every sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven men, but the blasphemy of the Spirit shall not be forgiven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.32"><v id="32"></v>And whosoever shall speak a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but he that shall speak against the Holy Ghost, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this world, nor in the world to come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.33"><v id="33"></v>Either make the tree good and its fruit good: or make the tree evil, and its fruit evil. For by the fruit the tree is known. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.34"><v id="34"></v>O generation of vipers, how can you speak good things, whereas you are evil? for out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.35"><v id="35"></v>A good man out of a good treasure bringeth forth good things: and an evil man out of an evil treasure bringeth forth evil things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.36"><v id="36"></v>But I say unto you, that every idle word that men shall speak, they shall render an account for it in the day of judgment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.37"><v id="37"></v>For by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.38"><v id="38"></v>Then some of the scribes and Pharisees answered him, saying: Master we would see a sign from thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.39"><v id="39"></v>Who answering said to them: An evil and adulterous generation seeketh a sign: and a sign shall not be given it, but the sign of Jonas the prophet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.40"><v id="40"></v>For as Jonas was in the whale's belly three days and three nights: so shall the Son of man be in the heart of the earth three days and three nights. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.41"><v id="41"></v>The men of Ninive shall rise in judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: because they did penance at the preaching of Jonas. And behold a greater than Jonas here. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.42"><v id="42"></v>The queen of the south shall rise in judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon, and behold a greater than Solomon here. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.43"><v id="43"></v>And when an unclean spirit is gone out of a man he walketh through dry places seeking rest, and findeth none. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.44"><v id="44"></v>Then he saith: I will return into my house from whence I came out. And coming he findeth it empty, swept, and garnished. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.45"><v id="45"></v>Then he goeth, and taketh with him seven other spirits more wicked than himself, and they enter in and dwell there: and the last state of that man in made worse than the first. So shall it be also to this wicked generation. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.46"><v id="46"></v>As he was yet speaking to the multitudes, behold his mother and his brethren stood without, seeking to speak to him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.47"><v id="47"></v>And one said unto him: Behold thy mother and thy brethren stand without, seeking thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.48"><v id="48"></v>But he answering him that told him, said: Who is my mother, and who are my brethren? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.49"><v id="49"></v>And stretching forth his hand towards his disciples, he said: Behold my mother and my brethren. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.12.50"><v id="50"></v>For whosoever shall do the will of my Father, that is in heaven, he is my brother, and sister, and mother. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.13.0-40.13.0">
<bcv bcv="40.13.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="13"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.1"><v id="1"></v>THE same day Jesus going out of the house, sat by the sea side. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.2"><v id="2"></v>And great multitudes were gathered unto him, so that he went up into a boat and sat: and all the multitude stood on the shore. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.3"><v id="3"></v>And he spoke to them many things in parables, saying: Behold the sower went forth to sow. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.4"><v id="4"></v>And whilst he soweth some fell by the way side, and the birds of the air came and ate them up. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.5"><v id="5"></v>And other some fell upon stony ground, where they had not much earth: and they sprung up immediately, because they had no deepness of earth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.6"><v id="6"></v>And when the sun was up they were scorched: and because they had not root, they withered away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.7"><v id="7"></v>And others fell among thorns: and the thorns grew up and choked them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.8"><v id="8"></v>And others fell upon good ground: and they brought forth fruit, some an hundredfold, some sixtyfold, and some thirtyfold. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.9"><v id="9"></v>He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.10"><v id="10"></v>And his disciples came and said to him: Why speakest thou to them in parables? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.11"><v id="11"></v>Who answered and said to them: Because to you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven: but to them it is not given. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.12"><v id="12"></v>For he that hath, to him shall be given, and he shall abound: but he that hath not, from him shall be taken away that also which he hath. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.13"><v id="13"></v>Therefore do I speak to them in parables: because seeing they see not, and hearing they hear not, neither do they understand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.14"><v id="14"></v>And the prophecy of Isaias is fulfilled in them, who saith: By hearing you shall hear, and shall not understand: and seeing you shall see, and shall not perceive. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.15"><v id="15"></v>For the heart of this people is grown gross, and with their ears they have been dull of hearing, and their eyes they have shut: lest at any time they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and be converted, and I should heal them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.16"><v id="16"></v>But blessed are your eyes, because they see, and your ears, because they hear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.17"><v id="17"></v>For, amen, I say to you, many prophets and just men have desired to see the things that you see, and have not seen them, and to hear the things that you hear and have not heard them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.18"><v id="18"></v>Hear you therefore the parable of the sower. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.19"><v id="19"></v>When any one heareth the word of the kingdom, and understandeth it not, there cometh the wicked one, and catcheth away that which was sown in his heart: this is he that received the seed by the way side. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.20"><v id="20"></v>And he that received the seed upon stony ground, is he that heareth the word, and immediately receiveth it with joy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.21"><v id="21"></v>Yet hath he not root in himself, but is only for a time: and when there ariseth tribulation and persecution because of the word, he is presently scandalized. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.22"><v id="22"></v>And he that received the seed among thorns, is he that heareth the word, and the care of this world and the deceitfulness of riches choketh up the word, and he becometh fruitless. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.23"><v id="23"></v>But he that received the seed upon good ground, is he that heareth the word, and understandeth, and beareth fruit, and yieldeth the one an hundredfold, and another sixty, and another thirty. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.24"><v id="24"></v>Another parable he proposed to them, saying: The kingdom of heaven is likened to a man that sowed good seeds in his field. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.25"><v id="25"></v>But while men were asleep, his enemy came and oversowed cockle among the wheat and went his way. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.26"><v id="26"></v>And when the blade was sprung up, and had brought forth fruit, then appeared also the cockle. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.27"><v id="27"></v>And the servants of the goodman of the house coming said to him: Sir, didst thou not sow good seed in thy field? whence then hath it cockle? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.28"><v id="28"></v>And he said to them: An enemy hath done this. And the servants said to him: Wilt thou that we go and gather it up? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.29"><v id="29"></v>And he said: No, lest perhaps gathering up the cockle, you root up the wheat also together with it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.30"><v id="30"></v>Suffer both to grow until the harvest, and in the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers: Gather up first the cockle, and bind it into bundles to burn, but the wheat gather ye into my barn. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.31"><v id="31"></v>Another parable he proposed unto them, saying: The kingdom of heaven is like to a grain of mustard seed, which a man took and sowed in his field. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.32"><v id="32"></v>Which is the least indeed of all seeds; but when it is grown up, it is greater than all herbs, and becometh a tree, so that the birds of the air come, and dwell in the branches thereof. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.33"><v id="33"></v>Another parable he spoke to them: The kingdom of heaven is like to leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of meal, until the whole was leavened. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.34"><v id="34"></v>All these things Jesus spoke in parables to the multitudes: and without parables he did not speak to them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.35"><v id="35"></v>That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying: I will open my mouth in parables, I will utter things hidden from the foundation of the world. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.36"><v id="36"></v>Then having sent away the multitudes, he came into the house, and his disciples came to him, saying: Expound to us the parable of the cockle of the field. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.37"><v id="37"></v>Who made answer and said to them: He that soweth the good seed, is the Son of man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.38"><v id="38"></v>And the field, is the world. And the good seed are the children of the kingdom. And the cockle, are the children of the wicked one. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.39"><v id="39"></v>And the enemy that sowed them, is the devil. But the harvest is the end of the world. And the reapers are the angels. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.40"><v id="40"></v>Even as cockle therefore is gathered up, and burnt with fire: so shall it be at the end of the world. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.41"><v id="41"></v>The Son of man shall send his angels, and they shall gather out of his kingdom all scandals, and them that work iniquity. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.42"><v id="42"></v>And shall cast them into the furnace of fire: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.43"><v id="43"></v>Then shall the just shine as the sun, in the kingdom of their Father. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.44"><v id="44"></v>The kingdom of heaven is like unto a treasure hidden in a field. Which a man having found, hid it, and for joy thereof goeth, and selleth all that he hath, and buyeth that field. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.45"><v id="45"></v>Again the kingdom of heaven is like to a merchant seeking good pearls. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.46"><v id="46"></v>Who when he had found one pearl of great price, went his way, and sold all that he had, and bought it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.47"><v id="47"></v>Again the kingdom of heaven is like to a net cast into the sea, and gathering together of all kind of fishes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.48"><v id="48"></v>Which, when it was filled, they drew out, and sitting by the shore, they chose out the good into vessels, but the bad they cast forth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.49"><v id="49"></v>So shall it be at the end of the world. The angels shall go out, and shall separate the wicked from among the just. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.50"><v id="50"></v>And shall cast them into the furnace of fire: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.51"><v id="51"></v>Have ye understood all these things? They say to him: Yes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.52"><v id="52"></v>He said unto them: Therefore every scribe instructed in the kingdom of heaven, is like to a man that is a householder, who bringeth forth out of his treasure new things and old. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.53"><v id="53"></v>And it came to pass: when Jesus had finished these parables, he passed from thence. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.54"><v id="54"></v>And coming into his own country, he taught them in their synagogues, so that they wondered and said: How came this man by this wisdom and miracles? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.55"><v id="55"></v>Is not this the carpenter's son? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brethren James, and Joseph, and Simon, and Jude: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.56"><v id="56"></v>And his sisters, are they not all with us? Whence therefore hath he all these things? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.57"><v id="57"></v>And they were scandalized in his regard. But Jesus said to them: A prophet is not without honour, save in his own country, and in his own house. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.13.58"><v id="58"></v>And he wrought not many miracles there, because of their unbelief. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.14.0-40.14.0">
<bcv bcv="40.14.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="14"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.1"><v id="1"></v>AT that time Herod the Tetrarch heard the fame of Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.2"><v id="2"></v>And he said to his servants: This is John the Baptist: he is risen from the dead, and therefore mighty works shew forth themselves in him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.3"><v id="3"></v>For Herod had apprehended John and bound him, and put him into prison, because of Herodias, his brother's wife. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.4"><v id="4"></v>For John said to him: It is not lawful for thee to have her. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.5"><v id="5"></v>And having a mind to put him to death, he feared the people: because they esteemed him as a prophet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.6"><v id="6"></v>But on Herod's birthday, the daughter of Herodias danced before them: and pleased Herod. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.7"><v id="7"></v>Whereupon he promised with an oath, to give her whatsoever she would ask of him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.8"><v id="8"></v>But she being instructed before by her mother, said: Give me here in a dish the head of John the Baptist. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.9"><v id="9"></v>And the king was struck sad: yet because of his oath, and for them that sat with him at table, he commanded it to be given. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.10"><v id="10"></v>And he sent, and beheaded John in the prison. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.11"><v id="11"></v>And his head was brought in a dish: and it was given to the damsel, and she brought it to her mother. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.12"><v id="12"></v>And his disciples came and took the body, and buried it, and came and told Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.13"><v id="13"></v>Which when Jesus had heard, he retired from thence by boat, into a desert place apart, and the multitudes having heard of it, followed him on foot out of the cities. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.14"><v id="14"></v>And he coming forth saw a great multitude, and had compassion on them, and healed their sick. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.15"><v id="15"></v>And when it was evening, his disciples came to him, saying: This is a desert place, and the hour is now past: send away the multitudes, that going into the towns, they may buy themselves victuals. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.16"><v id="16"></v>But Jesus said to them, They have no need to go: give you them to eat. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.17"><v id="17"></v>They answered him: We have not here, but five loaves, and two fishes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.18"><v id="18"></v>He said to them: Bring them hither to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.19"><v id="19"></v>And when he had commanded the multitudes to sit down upon the grass, he took the five loaves and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed, and brake, and gave the loaves to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitudes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.20"><v id="20"></v>And they did all eat, and were filled. And they took up what remained, twelve full baskets of fragments. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.21"><v id="21"></v>And the number of them that did eat, was five thousand men, besides women and children. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.22"><v id="22"></v>And forthwith Jesus obliged his disciples to go up into the boat, and to go before him over the water, till he dismissed the people. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.23"><v id="23"></v>And having dismissed the multitude, he went into a mountain alone to pray. And when it was evening, he was there alone. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.24"><v id="24"></v>But the boat in the midst of the sea was tossed with the waves: for the wind was contrary. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.25"><v id="25"></v>And in the fourth watch of the night, he came to them walking upon the sea. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.26"><v id="26"></v>And they seeing him walk upon the sea, were troubled, saying: It is an apparition. And they cried out for fear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.27"><v id="27"></v>And immediately Jesus spoke to them, saying: Be of good heart: it is I, fear ye not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.28"><v id="28"></v>And Peter making answer, said: Lord, if it be thou, bid me come to thee upon the waters. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.29"><v id="29"></v>And he said: Come. And Peter going down out of the boat, walked upon the water to come to Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.30"><v id="30"></v>But seeing the wind strong, he was afraid: and when he began to sink, he cried out, saying: Lord, save me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.31"><v id="31"></v>And immediately Jesus stretching forth his hand took hold of him, and said to him: O thou of little faith, why didst thou doubt? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.32"><v id="32"></v>And when they were come up into the boat, the wind ceased. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.33"><v id="33"></v>And they that were in the boat came and adored him, saying: Indeed thou art the Son of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.34"><v id="34"></v>And having passed the water, they came into the country of Genesar. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.35"><v id="35"></v>And when the men of that place had knowledge of him, they sent into all that country, and brought to him all that were diseased. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.14.36"><v id="36"></v>And they besought him that they might touch but the hem of his garment. And as many as touched, were made whole. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.15.0-40.15.0">
<bcv bcv="40.15.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="15"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.1"><v id="1"></v>THEN came to him from Jerusalem scribes and Pharisees, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.2"><v id="2"></v>Why do thy disciples trangress the tradition of the ancients? For they wash not their hands when they eat bread. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.3"><v id="3"></v>But he answering, said to them: Why do you also transgress the commandment of God for your tradition? For God said: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.4"><v id="4"></v>Honour thy father and mother: And: He that shall curse father or mother, let him die the death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.5"><v id="5"></v>But you say: Whosoever shall say to father or mother, The gift whatsoever proceedeth from me, shall profit thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.6"><v id="6"></v>And he shall not honour his father or his mother: and you have made void the commandment of God for your tradition. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.7"><v id="7"></v>Hypocrites, well hath Isaias prophesied of you, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.8"><v id="8"></v>This people honoureth me with their lips: but their heart is far from me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.9"><v id="9"></v>And in vain do they worship me, teaching doctrines and commandments of men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.10"><v id="10"></v>And having called together the multitudes unto him, he said to them: Hear ye and understand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.11"><v id="11"></v>Not that which goeth into the mouth defileth a man: but what cometh out of the mouth, this defileth a man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.12"><v id="12"></v>Then came his disciples, and said to him: Dost thou know that the Pharisees, when they heard this word, were scandalized? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.13"><v id="13"></v>But he answering them, said: Every plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted, shall be rooted up. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.14"><v id="14"></v>Let them alone: they are blind, and leaders of the blind. And if the blind lead the blind, both will fall into the pit. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.15"><v id="15"></v>And Peter answering, said to him: Expound to us this parable. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.16"><v id="16"></v>But he said: Are you also yet without understanding? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.17"><v id="17"></v>Do you not understand, that whatsoever entereth into the mouth, goeth into the belly, and is cast out into the privy? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.18"><v id="18"></v>But the things which proceed out of the mouth, come forth from the heart, and those things defile a man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.19"><v id="19"></v>For from the heart come forth evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false testimonies, blasphemies. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.20"><v id="20"></v>These are the things that defile a man. But to eat with unwashed hands doth not defile a man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.21"><v id="21"></v>And Jesus went from thence, and retired into the coasts of Tyre and Sidon. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.22"><v id="22"></v>And behold a woman of Canaan who came out of those coasts, crying out, said to him: Have mercy on me, O Lord, thou son of David: my daughter is grieviously troubled by the devil. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.23"><v id="23"></v>Who answered her not a word. And his disciples came and besought him, saying: Send her away, for she crieth after us: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.24"><v id="24"></v>And he answering, said: I was not sent but to the sheep that are lost of the house of Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.25"><v id="25"></v>But she came and adored him, saying: Lord, help me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.26"><v id="26"></v>Who answering, said: It is not good to take the bread of the children, and to cast it to the dogs. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.27"><v id="27"></v>But she said: Yea, Lord; for the whelps also eat of the crumbs that fall from the table of their masters. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.28"><v id="28"></v>Then Jesus answering, said to her: O woman, great is thy faith: be it done to thee as thou wilt: and her daughter was cured from that hour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.29"><v id="29"></v>And when Jesus had passed away from thence, he came nigh the sea of Galilee. And going up into a mountain, he sat there. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.30"><v id="30"></v>And there came to him great multitudes, having with them the dumb, the blind, the lame, the maimed, and many others: and they cast them down at his feet, and he healed them: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.31"><v id="31"></v>So that the multitudes marvelled seeing the dumb speak, the lame walk, and the blind see: and they glorified the God of Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.32"><v id="32"></v>And Jesus called together his disciples, and said: I have compassion on the multitudes, because they continue with me now three days, and have not what to eat, and I will not send them away fasting, lest they faint in the way. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.33"><v id="33"></v>And the disciples say unto him: Whence then should we have so many loaves in the desert, as to fill so great a multitude? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.34"><v id="34"></v>And Jesus said to them: How many loaves have you? But they said: Seven, and a few little fishes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.35"><v id="35"></v>And he commanded the multitude to sit down upon the ground. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.36"><v id="36"></v>And taking the seven loaves and the fishes, and giving thanks, he brake, and gave to his disciples, and the disciples to the people. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.37"><v id="37"></v>And they did all eat, and had their fill. And they took up seven baskets full, of what remained of the fragments. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.38"><v id="38"></v>And they that did eat, were four thousand men, beside children and women. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.15.39"><v id="39"></v>And having dismissed the multitude, he went up into a boat, and came into the coasts of Magedan. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.16.0-40.16.0">
<bcv bcv="40.16.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="16"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.1"><v id="1"></v>AND there came to him the Pharisees and Sadduccees tempting: and they asked him to shew them a sign from heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.2"><v id="2"></v>But he answered and said to them: When it is evening, you say, It will be fair weather, for the sky is red. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.3"><v id="3"></v>And in the morning: To day there will be a storm, for the sky is red and lowering. You know then how to discern the face of the sky: and can you not know the signs of the times? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.4"><v id="4"></v>A wicked and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign: and a sign shall not be given it, but the sign of Jonas the prophet. And he left them, and went away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.5"><v id="5"></v>And when his disciples were come over the water, they had forgotten to take bread. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.6"><v id="6"></v>Who said to them: Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.7"><v id="7"></v>But they thought within themselves, saying: Because we have taken no bread. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.8"><v id="8"></v>And Jesus knowing it, said: Why do you think within yourselves, O ye of little faith, for that you have no bread? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.9"><v id="9"></v>Do you not yet understand, neither do you remember the five loaves among five thousand men, and how many baskets you took up? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.10"><v id="10"></v>Nor the seven loaves among four thousand men, and how many baskets you took up? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.11"><v id="11"></v>Why do you not understand that it was not concerning the bread I said to you: Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.12"><v id="12"></v>Then they understood that he said not that they should beware of the leaven of bread, but of the doctrine of the Pharisees and Sadducees. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.13"><v id="13"></v>And Jesus came into the quarters of Cesarea Philippi: and he asked his disciples, saying: Whom do men say that the Son of man is? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.14"><v id="14"></v>But they said: Some John the Baptist, and other some Elias, and others Jeremias, or one of the prophets. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.15"><v id="15"></v>Jesus saith to them: But whom do you say that I am? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.16"><v id="16"></v>Simon Peter answered and said: Thou art Christ, the Son of the living God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.17"><v id="17"></v>And Jesus answering, said to him: Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-Jona: because flesh and blood hath not revealed it to thee, but my Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.18"><v id="18"></v>And I say to thee: That thou art Peter; and upon this rock I will build my church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.19"><v id="19"></v>And I will give to thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven. And whatsoever thou shalt bind upon earth, it shall be bound also in heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt loose upon earth, it shall be loosed also in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.20"><v id="20"></v>Then he commanded his disciples, that they should tell no one that he was Jesus the Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.21"><v id="21"></v>From that time Jesus began to shew to his disciples, that he must go to Jerusalem, and suffer many things from the ancients and scribes and chief priests, and be put to death, and the third day rise again. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.22"><v id="22"></v>And Peter taking him, began to rebuke him, saying: Lord, be it far from thee, this shall not be unto thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.23"><v id="23"></v>Who turning, said to Peter: Go behind me, Satan, thou art a scandal unto me: because thou savourest not the things that are of God, but the things that are of men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.24"><v id="24"></v>Then Jesus said to his disciples: If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.25"><v id="25"></v>For he that will save his life, shall lose it: and he that shall lose his life for my sake, shall find it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.26"><v id="26"></v>For what doth it profit a man, if he gain the whole world, and suffer the loss of his own soul? Or what exchange shall a man give for his soul? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.27"><v id="27"></v>For the Son of man shall come in the glory of his Father with his angels: and then will he render to every man according to his works. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.16.28"><v id="28"></v>Amen I say to you, there are some of them that stand here, that shall not taste death, till they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.17.0-40.17.0">
<bcv bcv="40.17.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="17"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.1"><v id="1"></v>AND after six days Jesus taketh unto him Peter and James, and John his brother, and bringeth them up into a high mountain apart: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.2"><v id="2"></v>And he was transfigured before them. And his face did shine as the sun: and his garments became white as snow. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.3"><v id="3"></v>And behold there appeared to them Moses and Elias talking with him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.4"><v id="4"></v>And Peter answering, said to Jesus: Lord, it is good for us to be here: if thou wilt, let us make here three tabernacles, one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.5"><v id="5"></v>And as he was yet speaking, behold a bright cloud overshadowed them. And lo, a voice out of the cloud, saying: This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased: hear ye him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.6"><v id="6"></v>And the disciples hearing, fell upon their face, and were very much afraid. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.7"><v id="7"></v>And Jesus came and touched them: and said to them, Arise, and fear not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.8"><v id="8"></v>And they lifting up their eyes saw no one but only Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.9"><v id="9"></v>And as they came down from the mountain, Jesus charged them, saying: Tell the vision to no man, till the Son of man be risen from the dead. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.10"><v id="10"></v>And his disciples asked him, saying: Why then do the scribes say that Elias must come first? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.11"><v id="11"></v>But he answering, said to them: Elias indeed shall come, and restore all things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.12"><v id="12"></v>But I say to you, that Elias is already come, and they knew him not, but have done unto him whatsoever they had a mind. So also the Son of man shall suffer from them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.13"><v id="13"></v>Then the disciples understood, that he had spoken to them of John the Baptist. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.14"><v id="14"></v>And when he was come to the multitude, there came to him a man falling down on his knees before him, saying: Lord, have pity on my son, for he is a lunatic, and suffereth much: for he falleth often into the fire, and often into the water. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.15"><v id="15"></v>And I brought him to thy disciples, and they could not cure him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.16"><v id="16"></v>Then Jesus answered and said: O unbelieving and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you? How long shall I suffer you? bring him hither to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.17"><v id="17"></v>And Jesus rebuked him, and the devil went out of him, and the child was cured from that hour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.18"><v id="18"></v>Then came the disciples to Jesus secretly, and said: Why could not we cast him out? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.19"><v id="19"></v>Jesus said to them: Because of your unbelief. For, amen I say to you, if you have faith as a grain of mustard seed, you shall say to this mountain, Remove from hence hither, and it shall remove; and nothing shall be impossible to you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.20"><v id="20"></v>But this kind is not cast out but by prayer and fasting. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.21"><v id="21"></v>And when they abode together in Galilee, Jesus said to them: The Son of man shall be betrayed into the hands of men: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.22"><v id="22"></v>And they shall kill him, and the third day he shall rise again. And they were troubled exceedingly. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.23"><v id="23"></v>And when they were come to Capharnaum, they that recieved the didrachmas, came to Peter and said to him: Doth not your master pay the didrachmas? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.24"><v id="24"></v>He said: Yes. And when he was come into the house, Jesus prevented him, saying: What is thy opinion, Simon? The kings of the earth, of whom do they receive tribute or custom? of their own children, or of strangers? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.25"><v id="25"></v>And he said: Of strangers. Jesus said to him: Then the children are free. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.17.26"><v id="26"></v>But that we may not scandalize them, go to the sea, and cast in a hook: and that fish which shall first come up, take: and when thou hast opened its mouth, thou shalt find a stater: take that, and give it to them for me and thee. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.18.0-40.18.0">
<bcv bcv="40.18.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="18"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.1"><v id="1"></v>AT that hour the disciples came to Jesus, saying: Who thinkest thou is the greater in the kingdom of heaven? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.2"><v id="2"></v>And Jesus calling unto him a little child, set him in the midst of them, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.3"><v id="3"></v>And said: Amen I say to you, unless you be converted, and become as little children, you shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.4"><v id="4"></v>Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, he is the greater in the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.5"><v id="5"></v>And he that shall receive one such little child in my name, receiveth me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.6"><v id="6"></v>But he that shall scandalize one of these little ones that believe in me, it were better for him that a millstone should be hanged about his neck, and that he should be drowned in the depth of the sea. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.7"><v id="7"></v>Woe to the world because of scandals. For it must needs be that scandals come: but nevertheless woe to that man by whom the scandal cometh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.8"><v id="8"></v>And if thy hand, or thy foot scandalize thee, cut it off, and cast it from thee. It is better for thee to go into life maimed or lame, than having two hands or two feet, to be cast into everlasting fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.9"><v id="9"></v>And if thy eye scandalize thee, pluck it out, and cast it from thee. It is better for thee having one eye to enter into life, than having two eyes to be cast into hell fire. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.10"><v id="10"></v>See that you despise not one of these little ones: for I say to you, that their angels in heaven always see the face of my Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.11"><v id="11"></v>For the Son of man is come to save that which was lost. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.12"><v id="12"></v>What think you? If a man have an hundred sheep, and one of them should go astray: doth he not leave the ninety-nine in the mountains, and go to seek that which is gone astray? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.13"><v id="13"></v>And if it so be that he find it: Amen I say to you, he rejoiceth more for that, than for the ninety-nine that went not astray. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.14"><v id="14"></v>Even so it is not the will of your Father, who is in heaven, that one of these little ones should perish. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.15"><v id="15"></v>But if thy brother shall offend against thee, go, and rebuke him between thee and him alone. If he shall hear thee, thou shalt gain thy brother. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.16"><v id="16"></v>And if he will not hear thee, take with thee one or two more: that in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may stand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.17"><v id="17"></v>And if he will not hear them: tell the church. And if he will not hear the church, let him be to thee as the heathen and publican. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.18"><v id="18"></v>Amen I say to you, whatsoever you shall bind upon earth, shall be bound also in heaven; and whatsoever you shall loose upon earth, shall be loosed also in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.19"><v id="19"></v>Again I say to you, that if two of you shall consent upon earth, concerning any thing whatsoever they shall ask, it shall be done to them by my Father who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.20"><v id="20"></v>For where there are two or three gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.21"><v id="21"></v>Then came Peter unto him and said: Lord, how often shall my brother offend against me, and I forgive him? till seven times? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.22"><v id="22"></v>Jesus saith to him: I say not to thee, till seven times; but till seventy times seven times. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.23"><v id="23"></v>Therefore is the kingdom of heaven likened to a king, who would take an account of his servants. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.24"><v id="24"></v>And when he had begun to take the account, one was brought to him, that owed him ten thousand talents. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.25"><v id="25"></v>And as he had not wherewith to pay it, his lord commanded that he should be sold, and his wife and children and all that he had, and payment to be made. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.26"><v id="26"></v>But that servant falling down, besought him, saying: Have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.27"><v id="27"></v>And the lord of that servant being moved with pity, let him go and forgave him the debt. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.28"><v id="28"></v>But when that servant was gone out, he found one of his fellow servants that owed him an hundred pence: and laying hold of him, throttled him, saying: Pay what thou owest. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.29"><v id="29"></v>And his fellow servant falling down, besought him, saying: Have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.30"><v id="30"></v>And he would not: but went and cast him into prison, till he paid the debt. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.31"><v id="31"></v>Now his fellow servants seeing what was done, were very much grieved, and they came and told their lord all that was done. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.32"><v id="32"></v>Then his lord called him; and said to him: Thou wicked servant, I forgave thee all the debt, because thou besoughtest me: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.33"><v id="33"></v>Shouldst not thou then have had compassion also on thy fellow servant, even as I had compassion on thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.34"><v id="34"></v>And his lord being angry, delivered him to the torturers until he paid all the debt. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.18.35"><v id="35"></v>So also shall my heavenly Father do to you, if you forgive not every one his brother from your hearts. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.19.0-40.19.0">
<bcv bcv="40.19.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="19"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.1"><v id="1"></v>AND it came to pass when Jesus had ended these words, he departed from Galilee, and came into the coasts of Judea, beyond Jordan. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.2"><v id="2"></v>And great multitudes followed him: and he healed them there. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.3"><v id="3"></v>And there came to him the Pharisees tempting him, and saying: Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.4"><v id="4"></v>Who answering, said to them: Have ye not read, that he who made man from the beginning, Made them male and female? And he said: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.5"><v id="5"></v>For this cause shall a man leave father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife, and they two shall be in one flesh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.6"><v id="6"></v>Therefore now they are not two, but one flesh. What therefore God hath joined together, let no man put asunder. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.7"><v id="7"></v>They say to him: Why then did Moses command to give a bill of divorce, and to put away? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.8"><v id="8"></v>He saith to them: Because Moses by reason of the hardness of your heart permitted you to put away your wives: but from the beginning it was not so. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.9"><v id="9"></v>And I say to you, that whosoever shall put away his wife, except it be for fornication, and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and he that shall marry her that is put away, committeth adultery. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.10"><v id="10"></v>His disciples say unto him: If the case of a man with his wife be so, it is not expedient to marry. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.11"><v id="11"></v>Who said to them: All men take not this word, but they to whom it is given. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.12"><v id="12"></v>For there are eunuchs, who were born so from their mother's womb: and there are eunuchs, who were made so by men: and there are eunuchs, who have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven. He that can take, let him take it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.13"><v id="13"></v>Then were little children presented to him, that he should impose hands upon them and pray. And the disciples rebuked them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.14"><v id="14"></v>But Jesus said to them: Suffer the little children, and forbid them not to come to me: for the kingdom of heaven is for such. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.15"><v id="15"></v>And when he had imposed hands upon them, he departed from thence. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.16"><v id="16"></v>And behold one came and said to him: Good master, what good shall I do that I may have life everlasting? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.17"><v id="17"></v>Who said to him: Why asketh thou me concerning good? One is good, God. But if thou wilt enter into life, keep the commandments. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.18"><v id="18"></v>He said to him: Which? And Jesus said: Thou shalt do no murder, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.19"><v id="19"></v>Honour thy father and thy mother: and, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.20"><v id="20"></v>The young man saith to him: All these I have kept from my youth, what is yet wanting to me? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.21"><v id="21"></v>Jesus saith to him: If thou wilt be perfect, go sell what thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come follow me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.22"><v id="22"></v>And when the young man had heard this word, he went away sad: for he had great possessions. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.23"><v id="23"></v>Then Jesus said to his disciples: Amen, I say to you, that a rich man shall hardly enter into the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.24"><v id="24"></v>And again I say to you: It is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.25"><v id="25"></v>And when they had heard this, the disciples wondered very much, saying: Who then can be saved? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.26"><v id="26"></v>And Jesus beholding, said to them: With men this is impossible: but with God all things are possible. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.27"><v id="27"></v>Then Peter answering, said to him: Behold we have left all things, and have followed thee: what therefore shall we have? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.28"><v id="28"></v>And Jesus said to them: Amen, I say to you, that you, who have followed me, in the regeneration, when the Son of man shall sit on the seat of his majesty, you also shall sit on twelve seats judging the twelve tribes of Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.29"><v id="29"></v>And every one that hath left house, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my name's sake, shall receive an hundredfold, and shall possess life everlasting. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.19.30"><v id="30"></v>And many that are first, shall be last: and the last shall be first. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.20.0-40.20.0">
<bcv bcv="40.20.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="20"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.1"><v id="1"></v>THE kingdom of heaven is like to an householder, who went out early in the morning to hire labourers into his vineyard. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.2"><v id="2"></v>And having agreed with the labourers for a penny a day, he sent them into his vineyard. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.3"><v id="3"></v>And going about the third hour, he saw others standing in the market place idle. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.4"><v id="4"></v>And he said to them: Go you also into my vineyard, and I will give you what shall be just. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.5"><v id="5"></v>And they went their way. And again he went out about the sixth and the ninth hour, and did in like manner. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.6"><v id="6"></v>But about the eleventh hour he went out and found others standing, and he saith to them: Why stand you here all the day idle? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.7"><v id="7"></v>They say to him: Because no man hath hired us. He saith to them: Go you also into my vineyard. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.8"><v id="8"></v>And when evening was come, the lord of the vineyard saith to his steward: Call the labourers and pay them their hire, beginning from the last even to the first. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.9"><v id="9"></v>When therefore they were come, that came about the eleventh hour, they received every man a penny. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.10"><v id="10"></v>But when the first also came, they thought that they should receive more: and they also received every man a penny. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.11"><v id="11"></v>And receiving it they murmured against the master of the house, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.12"><v id="12"></v>Saying: These last have worked but one hour, and thou hast made them equal to us, that have borne the burden of the day and the heats. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.13"><v id="13"></v>But he answering said to one of them: Friend, I do thee no wrong: didst thou not agree with me for a penny? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.14"><v id="14"></v>Take what is thine, and go thy way: I will also give to this last even as to thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.15"><v id="15"></v>Or, is it not lawful for me to do what I will? is thy eye evil, because I am good? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.16"><v id="16"></v>So shall the last be first, and the first last. For many are called, but few chosen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.17"><v id="17"></v>And Jesus going up to Jerusalem, took the twelve disciples apart, and said to them: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.18"><v id="18"></v>Behold we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man shall be betrayed to the chief priests and the scribes, and they shall condemn him to death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.19"><v id="19"></v>And shall deliver him to the Gentiles to be mocked, and scourged, and crucified, and the third day he shall rise again. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.20"><v id="20"></v>Then came to him the mother of the sons of Zebedee with her sons, adoring and asking something of him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.21"><v id="21"></v>Who said to her: What wilt thou? She saith to him: Say that these my two sons may sit, the one on thy right hand, and the other on thy left, in thy kingdom. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.22"><v id="22"></v>And Jesus answering, said: You know not what you ask. Can you drink the chalice that I shall drink? They say to him: We can. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.23"><v id="23"></v>He saith to them: My chalice indeed you shall drink; but to sit on my right or left hand, is not mine to give to you, but to them for whom it is prepared by my Father. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.24"><v id="24"></v>And the ten hearing it, were moved with indignation against the two brethren. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.25"><v id="25"></v>But Jesus called them to him, and said: You know that the princes of the Gentiles lord it over them; and they that are the greater, exercise power upon them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.26"><v id="26"></v>It shall not be so among you: but whosoever will be the greater among you, let him be your minister: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.27"><v id="27"></v>And he that will be first among you, shall be your servant. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.28"><v id="28"></v>Even as the Son of man is not come to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a redemption for many. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.29"><v id="29"></v>And when they went out from Jericho, a great multitude followed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.30"><v id="30"></v>And behold two blind men sitting by the way side, heard that Jesus passed by, and they cried out, saying: O Lord, thou son of David, have mercy on us. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.31"><v id="31"></v>And the multitude rebuked them that they should hold their peace. But they cried out the more, saying: O Lord, thou son of David, have mercy on us. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.32"><v id="32"></v>And Jesus stood, and called them, and said: What will ye that I do to you? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.33"><v id="33"></v>They say to him: Lord, that our eyes be opened. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.20.34"><v id="34"></v>And Jesus having compassion on them, touched their eyes. And immediately they saw, and followed him. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.21.0-40.21.0">
<bcv bcv="40.21.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="21"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.1"><v id="1"></v>AND when they drew nigh to Jerusalem, and were come to Bethphage, unto mount Olivet, then Jesus sent two disciples, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.2"><v id="2"></v>Saying to them: Go ye into the village that is over against you, and immediately you shall find an ass tied, and a colt with her: loose them and bring them to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.3"><v id="3"></v>And if any man shall say anything to you, say ye, that the Lord hath need of them: and forthwith he will let them go. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.4"><v id="4"></v>Now all this was done that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.5"><v id="5"></v>Tell ye the daughter of Sion: Behold thy king cometh to thee, meek, and sitting upon an ass, and a colt the foal of her that is used to the yoke. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.6"><v id="6"></v>And the disciples going, did as Jesus commanded them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.7"><v id="7"></v>And they brought the ass and the colt, and laid their garments upon them, and made him sit thereon. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.8"><v id="8"></v>And a very great multitude spread their garments in the way: and others cut boughs from the trees, and strewed them in the way: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.9"><v id="9"></v>And the multitudes that went before and that followed, cried, saying: Hosanna to the son of David: Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord: Hosanna in the highest. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.10"><v id="10"></v>And when he was come into Jerusalem, the whole city was moved, saying: Who is this? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.11"><v id="11"></v>And the people said: This is Jesus the prophet, from Nazareth of Galilee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.12"><v id="12"></v>And Jesus went into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the money changers, and the chairs of them that sold doves: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.13"><v id="13"></v>And he saith to them: It is written, My house shall be called the house of prayer; but you have made it a den of thieves. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.14"><v id="14"></v>And there came to him the blind and the lame in the temple; and he healed them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.15"><v id="15"></v>And the chief priests and scribes, seeing the wonderful things that he did, and the children crying in the temple, and saying: Hosanna to the son of David; were moved with indignation. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.16"><v id="16"></v>And said to him: Hearest thou what these say? And Jesus said to them: Yea, have you never read: Out of the mouth of infants and of sucklings thou hast perfected praise? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.17"><v id="17"></v>And leaving them, he went out of the city into Bethania, and remained there. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.18"><v id="18"></v>And in the morning, returning into the city, he was hungry. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.19"><v id="19"></v>And seeing a certain fig tree by the way side, he came to it, and found nothing on it but leaves only, and he saith to it: May no fruit grow on thee henceforward for ever. And immediately the fig tree withered away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.20"><v id="20"></v>And the disciples seeing it wondered, saying: How is it presently withered away? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.21"><v id="21"></v>And Jesus answering, said to them: Amen, I say to you, if you shall have faith, and stagger not, not only this of the fig tree shall you do, but also if you shall say to this mountain, Take up and cast thyself into the sea, it shall be done. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.22"><v id="22"></v>And in all things whatsoever you shall ask in prayer, believing, you shall receive. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.23"><v id="23"></v>And when he was come into the temple, there came to him, as he was teaching, the chief priests and ancients of the people, saying: By what authority dost thou these things? and who hath given thee this authority? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.24"><v id="24"></v>Jesus answering, said to them: I also will ask you one word, which if you shall tell me, I will also tell you by what authority I do these things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.25"><v id="25"></v>The baptism of John, whence was it? from heaven or from men? But they thought within themselves, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.26"><v id="26"></v>If we shall say, from heaven, he will say to us: Why then did you not believe him? But if we shall say, from men, we are afraid of the multitude: for all held John as a prophet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.27"><v id="27"></v>And answering Jesus, they said: We know not. He also said to them: Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.28"><v id="28"></v>But what think you? A certain man had two sons; and coming to the first, he said: Son, go work to day in my vineyard. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.29"><v id="29"></v>And he answering, said: I will not. But afterwards, being moved with repentance, he went. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.30"><v id="30"></v>And coming to the other, he said in like manner. And he answering, said: I go, Sir; and he went not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.31"><v id="31"></v>Which of the two did the father's will? They say to him: The first. Jesus saith to them: Amen I say to you, that the publicans and the harlots shall go into the kingdom of God before you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.32"><v id="32"></v>For John came to you in the way of justice, and you did not believe him. But the publicans and the harlots believed him: but you, seeing it, did not even afterwards repent, that you might believe him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.33"><v id="33"></v>Hear ye another parable. There was a man an householder, who planted a vineyard, and made a hedge round about it, and dug in it a press, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen; and went into a strange country. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.34"><v id="34"></v>And when the time of the fruits drew nigh, he sent his servants to the husbandmen that they might receive the fruits thereof. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.35"><v id="35"></v>And the husbandmen laying hands on his servants, beat one, and killed another, and stoned another. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.36"><v id="36"></v>Again he sent other servants more than the former; and they did to them in like manner. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.37"><v id="37"></v>And last of all he sent to them his son, saying: They will reverence my son. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.38"><v id="38"></v>But the husbandmen seeing the son, said among themselves: This is the heir: come, let us kill him, and we shall have his inheritance. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.39"><v id="39"></v>And taking him, they cast him forth out of the vineyard, and killed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.40"><v id="40"></v>When therefore the lord of the vineyard shall come, what will he do to those husbandmen? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.41"><v id="41"></v>They say to him: He will bring those evil men to an evil end; and will let out his vineyard to other husbandmen, that shall render him the fruit in due season. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.42"><v id="42"></v>Jesus saith to them: Have you never read in the Scriptures: The stone which the builders rejected, the same is become the head of the corner? By the Lord this has been done; and it is wonderful in our eyes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.43"><v id="43"></v>Therefore I say to you, that the kingdom of God shall be taken from you, and shall be given to a nation yielding the fruits thereof. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.44"><v id="44"></v>And whosoever shall fall on this stone, shall be broken: but on whomsoever it shall fall, it shall grind him to powder. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.45"><v id="45"></v>And when the chief priests and Pharisees had heard his parables, they knew that he spoke of them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.21.46"><v id="46"></v>And seeking to lay hands on him, they feared the multitudes: because they held him as a prophet. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.22.0-40.22.0">
<bcv bcv="40.22.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="22"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.1"><v id="1"></v>AND Jesus answering, spoke again in parables to them, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.2"><v id="2"></v>The kingdom of heaven is likened to a king, who made a marriage for his son. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.3"><v id="3"></v>And he sent his servants, to call them that were invited to the marriage; and they would not come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.4"><v id="4"></v>Again he sent other servants, saying: Tell them that were invited, Behold, I have prepared my dinner; my beeves and fatlings are killed, and all things are ready: come ye to the marriage. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.5"><v id="5"></v>But they neglected, and went their own ways, one to his farm, and another to his merchandise. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.6"><v id="6"></v>And the rest laid hands on his servants, and having treated them contumeliously, put them to death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.7"><v id="7"></v>But when the king had heard of it, he was angry, and sending his armies, he destroyed those murderers, and burnt their city. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.8"><v id="8"></v>Then he saith to his servants: The marriage indeed is ready; but they that were invited were not worthy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.9"><v id="9"></v>Go ye therefore into the highways; and as many as you shall find, call to the marriage. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.10"><v id="10"></v>And his servants going forth into the ways, gathered together all that they found, both bad and good: and the marriage was filled with guests. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.11"><v id="11"></v>And the king went in to see the guests: and he saw there a man who had not on a wedding garment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.12"><v id="12"></v>And he saith to him: Friend, how camest thou in hither not having a wedding garment? But he was silent. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.13"><v id="13"></v>Then the king said to the waiters: Bind his hands and feet, and cast him into the exterior darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.14"><v id="14"></v>For many are called, but few are chosen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.15"><v id="15"></v>Then the Pharisees going, consulted among themselves how to insnare him in his speech. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.16"><v id="16"></v>And they sent to him their disciples with the Herodians, saying: Master, we know that thou art a true speaker, and teachest the way of God in truth, neither carest thou for any man: for thou dost not regard the person of men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.17"><v id="17"></v>Tell us therefore what dost thou think, is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar, or not? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.18"><v id="18"></v>But Jesus knowing their wickedness, said: Why do you tempt me, ye hypocrites? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.19"><v id="19"></v>Shew me the coin of the tribute. And they offered him a penny. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.20"><v id="20"></v>And Jesus saith to them: Whose image and inscription is this? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.21"><v id="21"></v>They say to him: Caesar's. Then he saith to them: Render therefore to Caesar the things that are Caesar's; and to God, the things that are God's. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.22"><v id="22"></v>And hearing this they wondered, and leaving him, went their ways. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.23"><v id="23"></v>That day there came to him the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection; and asked him, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.24"><v id="24"></v>Saying: Master, Moses said: If a man die having no son, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up issue to his brother. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.25"><v id="25"></v>Now there were with us seven brethren: and the first having married a wife, died; and not having issue, left his wife to his brother. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.26"><v id="26"></v>In like manner the second, and the third, and so on to the seventh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.27"><v id="27"></v>And last of all the woman died also. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.28"><v id="28"></v>At the resurrection therefore whose wife of the seven shall she be? for they all had her. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.29"><v id="29"></v>And Jesus answering, said to them: You err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.30"><v id="30"></v>For in the resurrection they shall neither marry nor be married; but shall be as the angels of God in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.31"><v id="31"></v>And concerning the resurrection of the dead, have you not read that which was spoken by God, saying to you: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.32"><v id="32"></v>I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? He is not the God of the dead, but of the living. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.33"><v id="33"></v>And the multitudes hearing it, were in admiration at his doctrine. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.34"><v id="34"></v>But the Pharisees hearing that he had silenced the Sadducees, came together: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.35"><v id="35"></v>And one of them, a doctor of the law, asking him, tempting him: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.36"><v id="36"></v>Master, which is the greatest commandment in the law? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.37"><v id="37"></v>Jesus said to him: Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul, and with thy whole mind. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.38"><v id="38"></v>This is the greatest and the first commandment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.39"><v id="39"></v>And the second is like to this: Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.40"><v id="40"></v>On these two commandments dependeth the whole law and the prophets. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.41"><v id="41"></v>And the Pharisees being gathered together, Jesus asked them, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.42"><v id="42"></v>Saying: What think you of Christ? whose son is he? They say to him: David's. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.43"><v id="43"></v>He saith to them: How then doth David in spirit call him Lord, saying: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.44"><v id="44"></v>The Lord said to my Lord, Sit on my right hand, until I make thy enemies thy footstool? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.45"><v id="45"></v>If David then call him Lord, how is he his son? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.22.46"><v id="46"></v>And no man was able to answer him a word; neither durst any man from that day forth ask him any more questions. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.23.0-40.23.0">
<bcv bcv="40.23.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="23"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.1"><v id="1"></v>THEN Jesus spoke to the multitudes and to his disciples, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.2"><v id="2"></v>Saying: The scribes and the Pharisees have sitten on the chair of Moses. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.3"><v id="3"></v>All things therefore whatsoever they shall say to you, observe and do: but according to their works do ye not; for they say, and do not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.4"><v id="4"></v>For they bind heavy and insupportable burdens, and lay them on men's shoulders; but with a finger of their own they will not move them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.5"><v id="5"></v>And all their works they do for to be seen of men. For they make their phylacteries broad, and enlarge their fringes. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.6"><v id="6"></v>And they love the first places at feasts, and the first chairs in the synagogues, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.7"><v id="7"></v>And salutations in the market place, and to be called by men, Rabbi. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.8"><v id="8"></v>But be not you called Rabbi. For one is your master; and all you are brethren. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.9"><v id="9"></v>And call none your father upon earth; for one is your father, who is in heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.10"><v id="10"></v>Neither be ye called masters; for one is you master, Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.11"><v id="11"></v>He that is the greatest among you shall be your servant. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.12"><v id="12"></v>And whosoever shall exalt himself shall be humbled: and he that shall humble himself shall be exalted. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.13"><v id="13"></v>But woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites; because you shut the kingdom of heaven against men, for you yourselves do not enter in; and those that are going in, you suffer not to enter. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.14"><v id="14"></v>Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites: because you devour the houses of widows, praying long prayers. For this you shall receive the greater judgment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.15"><v id="15"></v>Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites; because you go round about the sea and the land to make one proselyte; and when he is made, you make him the child of hell twofold more than yourselves. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.16"><v id="16"></v>Woe to you blind guides, that say, Whosoever shall swear by the temple, it is nothing; but he that shall swear by the gold of the temple, is a debtor. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.17"><v id="17"></v>Ye foolish and blind; for whether is greater, the gold, or the temple that sanctifieth the gold? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.18"><v id="18"></v>And whosoever shall swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gift that is upon it, is a debtor. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.19"><v id="19"></v>Ye blind: for whether is greater, the gift, or the altar that sanctifieth the gift? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.20"><v id="20"></v>He therefore that sweareth by the altar, sweareth by it, and by all things that are upon it: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.21"><v id="21"></v>And whosoever shall swear by temple, sweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth in it: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.22"><v id="22"></v>And he that sweareth by heaven, sweareth by the throne of God, and by him that sitteth thereon. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.23"><v id="23"></v>Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites; because you tithe mint, and anise, and cummin, and have left the weightier things of the law; judgment, and mercy, and faith. These things you ought to have done, and not to leave those undone. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.24"><v id="24"></v>Blind guides, who strain out a gnat, and swallow a camel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.25"><v id="25"></v>Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites; because you make clean the outside of the cup and of the dish, but within you are full of rapine and uncleanness. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.26"><v id="26"></v>Thou blind Pharisee, first make clean the inside of the cup and of the dish, that the outside may become clean. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.27"><v id="27"></v>Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites; because you are like to whited sepulchres, which outwardly appear to men beautiful, but within are full of dead men's bones, and of all filthiness. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.28"><v id="28"></v>So you also outwardly indeed appear to men just; but inwardly you are full of hypocrisy and iniquity. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.29"><v id="29"></v>Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites; that build the sepulchres of the prophets, and adorn the monuments of the just, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.30"><v id="30"></v>And say: If we had been in the days of our Fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.31"><v id="31"></v>Wherefore you are witnesses against yourselves, that you are the sons of them that killed the prophets. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.32"><v id="32"></v>Fill ye up then the measure of your fathers. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.33"><v id="33"></v>You serpents, generation of vipers, how will you flee from the judgment of hell? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.34"><v id="34"></v>Therefore behold I send to you prophets, and wise men, and scribes: and some of them you will put to death and crucify, and some you will scourge in your synagogues, and persecute from city to city: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.35"><v id="35"></v>That upon you may come all the just blood that hath been shed upon the earth, from the blood of Abel the just, even unto the blood of Zacharias the son of Barachias, whom you killed between the temple and the altar. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.36"><v id="36"></v>Amen I say to you, all these things shall come upon this generation. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.37"><v id="37"></v>Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, and stonest them that are sent unto thee, how often would I have gathered together thy children, as the hen doth gather her chickens under her wings, and thou wouldest not? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.38"><v id="38"></v>Behold, you house shall be left to you, desolate. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.23.39"><v id="39"></v>For I say to you, you shall not see me henceforth till you say: Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.24.0-40.24.0">
<bcv bcv="40.24.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="24"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.1"><v id="1"></v>AND Jesus being come out of the temple, went away. And his disciples came to shew him the buildings of the temple. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.2"><v id="2"></v>And he answering, said to them: Do you see all these things? Amen I say to you there shall not be left here a stone upon a stone that shall not be destroyed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.3"><v id="3"></v>And when he was sitting on mount Olivet, the disciples came to him privately, saying: Tell us when shall these things be? and what shall be the sign of thy coming, and of the consummation of the world? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.4"><v id="4"></v>And Jesus answering, said to them: Take heed that no man seduce you: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.5"><v id="5"></v>For many will come in my name saying, I am Christ: and they will seduce many. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.6"><v id="6"></v>And you shall hear of wars and rumours of wars. See that ye be not troubled. For these things must come to pass, but the end is not yet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.7"><v id="7"></v>For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; and there shall be pestilences, and famines, and earthquakes in places: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.8"><v id="8"></v>Now all these are the beginnings of sorrows. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.9"><v id="9"></v>Then shall they deliver you up to be afflicted, and shall put you to death: and you shall be hated by all nations for my name's sake. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.10"><v id="10"></v>And then shall many be scandalized: and shall betray one another: and shall hate one another. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.11"><v id="11"></v>And many false prophets shall rise, and shall seduce many. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.12"><v id="12"></v>And because iniquity hath abounded, the charity of many shall grow cold. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.13"><v id="13"></v>But he that shall persevere to the end, he shall be saved. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.14"><v id="14"></v>And this gospel of the kingdom, shall be preached in the whole world, for a testimony to all nations, and then shall the consummation come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.15"><v id="15"></v>When therefore you shall see the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place: he that readeth let him understand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.16"><v id="16"></v>Then they that are in Judea, let them flee to the mountains: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.17"><v id="17"></v>And he that is on the housetop, let him not come down to take any thing out of his house: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.18"><v id="18"></v>And he that is in the field, let him not go back to take his coat. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.19"><v id="19"></v>And woe to them that are with child, and that give suck in those days. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.20"><v id="20"></v>But pray that your flight be not in the winter, or on the sabbath. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.21"><v id="21"></v>For there shall be then great tribulation, such as hath not been from the beginning of the world until now, neither shall be. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.22"><v id="22"></v>And unless those days had been shortened, no flesh should be saved: but for the sake of the elect those days shall be shortened. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.23"><v id="23"></v>Then if any man shall say to you: Lo here is Christ, or there, do not believe him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.24"><v id="24"></v>For there shall arise false Christs and false prophets, and shall show great signs and wonders, insomuch as to deceive (if possible) even the elect. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.25"><v id="25"></v>Behold I have told it to you, beforehand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.26"><v id="26"></v>If therefore they shall say to you: Behold he is in the desert, go ye not out: Behold he is in the closets, believe it not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.27"><v id="27"></v>For as lightning cometh out of the east, and appeareth even into the west: so shall the coming of the Son of man be. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.28"><v id="28"></v>Wheresoever the body shall be, there shall the eagles also be gathered together. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.29"><v id="29"></v>And immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun shall be darkened and the moon shall not give her light, and the stars shall fall from heaven, and the powers of heaven shall be moved: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.30"><v id="30"></v>And then shall appear the sign of the Son of man in heaven: and then shall all tribes of the earth mourn: and they shall see the Son of man coming in the clouds of heaven with much power and majesty. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.31"><v id="31"></v>And he shall send his angels with a trumpet, and a great voice: and they shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from the farthest parts of the heavens to the utmost bounds of them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.32"><v id="32"></v>And from the fig tree learn a parable: When the branch thereof is now tender, and the leaves come forth, you know that summer is nigh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.33"><v id="33"></v>So you also, when you shall see all these things, know ye that it is nigh, even at the doors. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.34"><v id="34"></v>Amen I say to you, that this generation shall not pass, till all these things be done. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.35"><v id="35"></v>Heaven and earth shall pass, but my words shall not pass. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.36"><v id="36"></v>But of that day and hour no one knoweth, not the angels of heaven, but the Father alone. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.37"><v id="37"></v>And as in the days of Noe, so shall also the coming of the Son of man be. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.38"><v id="38"></v>For as in the days before the flood, they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, even till that day in which Noe entered into the ark, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.39"><v id="39"></v>And they knew not till the flood came, and took them all away; so also shall the coming of the Son of man be. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.40"><v id="40"></v>Then two shall be in the field: one shall be taken, and one shall be left. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.41"><v id="41"></v>Two women shall be grinding at the mill: one shall be taken, and one shall be left. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.42"><v id="42"></v>Watch ye therefore, because ye know not what hour your Lord will come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.43"><v id="43"></v>But know this ye, that if the goodman of the house knew at what hour the thief would come, he would certainly watch, and would not suffer his house to be broken open. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.44"><v id="44"></v>Wherefore be you also ready, because at what hour you know not the Son of man will come. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.45"><v id="45"></v>Who, thinkest thou, is a faithful and wise servant, whom his lord hath appointed over his family, to give them meat in season. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.46"><v id="46"></v>Blessed is that servant, whom when his lord shall come he shall find so doing. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.47"><v id="47"></v>Amen I say to you, he shall place him over all his goods. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.48"><v id="48"></v>But if that evil servant shall say in his heart: My lord is long a coming: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.49"><v id="49"></v>And shall begin to strike his fellow servants, and shall eat and drink with drunkards: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.50"><v id="50"></v>The lord of that servant shall come in a day that he hopeth not, and at an hour that he knoweth not: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.24.51"><v id="51"></v>And shall separate him, and appoint his portion with the hypocrites. There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.25.0-40.25.0">
<bcv bcv="40.25.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="25"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.1"><v id="1"></v>THEN shall the kingdom of heaven be like to ten virgins, who taking their lamps went out to meet the bridegroom and the bride. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.2"><v id="2"></v>And five of them were foolish, and five wise. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.3"><v id="3"></v>But the five foolish, having taken their lamps, did not take oil with them: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.4"><v id="4"></v>But the wise took oil in their vessels with the lamps. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.5"><v id="5"></v>And the bridegroom tarrying, they all slumbered and slept. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.6"><v id="6"></v>And at midnight there was a cry made: Behold the bridegroom cometh, go ye forth to meet him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.7"><v id="7"></v>Then all those virgins arose and trimmed their lamps. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.8"><v id="8"></v>And the foolish said to the wise: Give us of your oil, for our lamps are gone out. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.9"><v id="9"></v>The wise answered, saying: Lest perhaps there be not enough for us and for you, go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for yourselves. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.10"><v id="10"></v>Now whilst they went to buy, the bridegroom came: and they that were ready, went in with him to the marriage, and the door was shut. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.11"><v id="11"></v>But at last come also the other virgins, saying: Lord, Lord, open to us. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.12"><v id="12"></v>But he answering said: Amen I say to you, I know you not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.13"><v id="13"></v>Watch ye therefore, because you know not the day nor the hour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.14"><v id="14"></v>For even as a man going into a far country, called his servants, and delivered to them his goods; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.15"><v id="15"></v>And to one he gave five talents, and to another two, and to another one, to every one according to his proper ability: and immediately he took his journey. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.16"><v id="16"></v>And he that had received the five talents, went his way, and traded with the same, and gained other five. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.17"><v id="17"></v>And in like manner he that had received the two, gained other two. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.18"><v id="18"></v>But he that had received the one, going his way digged into the earth, and hid his lord's money. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.19"><v id="19"></v>But after a long time the lord of those servants came, and reckoned with them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.20"><v id="20"></v>And he that had received the five talents coming, brought other five talents, saying: Lord, thou didst deliver to me five talents, behold I have gained other five over and above. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.21"><v id="21"></v>His lord said to him: Well done, good and faithful servant, because thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will place thee over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.22"><v id="22"></v>And he also that had received the two talents came and said: Lord, thou deliveredst two talents to me: behold I have gained other two. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.23"><v id="23"></v>His lord said to him: Well done, good and faithful servant: because thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will place thee over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.24"><v id="24"></v>But he that had received the one talent, came and said: Lord, I know that thou art a hard man; thou reapest where thou hast not sown, and gatherest where thou hast not strewed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.25"><v id="25"></v>And being afraid I went and hid thy talent in the earth: behold here thou hast that which is thine. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.26"><v id="26"></v>And his lord answering, said to him: Wicked and slothful servant, thou knewest that I reap where I sow not, and gather where I have not strewed: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.27"><v id="27"></v>Thou oughtest therefore to have committed my money to the bankers, and at my coming I should have received my own with usury. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.28"><v id="28"></v>Take ye away therefore the talent from him, and give it to him that hath ten talents. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.29"><v id="29"></v>For to every one that hath shall be given, and he shall abound: but from him that hath not, that also which he seemeth to have shall be taken away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.30"><v id="30"></v>And the unprofitable servant cast ye out into the exterior darkness. There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.31"><v id="31"></v>And when the Son of man shall come in his majesty, and all the angels with him, then shall he sit upon the seat of his majesty. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.32"><v id="32"></v>And all nations shall be gathered together before him, and he shall separate them one from another, as the shepherd separateth the sheep from the goats: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.33"><v id="33"></v>And he shall set the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on his left. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.34"><v id="34"></v>Then shall the king say to them that shall be on his right hand: Come, ye blessed of my Father, possess you the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.35"><v id="35"></v>For I was hungry, and you gave me to eat; I was thirsty, and you gave me to drink; I was a stranger, and you took me in: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.36"><v id="36"></v>Naked, and you covered me: sick, and you visited me: I was in prison, and you came to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.37"><v id="37"></v>Then shall the just answer him, saying: Lord, when did we see thee hungry, and fed thee; thirsty, and gave thee drink? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.38"><v id="38"></v>And when did we see thee a stranger, and took thee in? or naked, and covered thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.39"><v id="39"></v>Or when did we see thee sick or in prison, and came to thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.40"><v id="40"></v>And the king answering, shall say to them: Amen I say to you, as long as you did it to one of these my least brethren, you did it to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.41"><v id="41"></v>Then he shall say to them also that shall be on his left hand: Depart from me, you cursed, into everlasting fire which was prepared for the devil and his angels. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.42"><v id="42"></v>For I was hungry, and you gave me not to eat: I was thirsty, and you gave me not to drink. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.43"><v id="43"></v>I was a stranger, and you took me not in: naked, and you covered me not: sick and in prison, and you did not visit me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.44"><v id="44"></v>Then they also shall answer him, saying: Lord, when did we see thee hungry, or thirsty, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister to thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.45"><v id="45"></v>Then he shall answer them, saying: Amen I say to you, as long as you did it not to one of these least, neither did you do it to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.25.46"><v id="46"></v>And these shall go into everlasting punishment: but the just, into life everlasting. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.26.0-40.26.0">
<bcv bcv="40.26.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="26"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.1"><v id="1"></v>AND it came to pass, when Jesus had ended all these words, he said to his disciples: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.2"><v id="2"></v>You know that after two days shall be the pasch, and the son of man shall be delivered up to be crucified: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.3"><v id="3"></v>Then were gathered together the chief priests and ancients of the people into the court of the high priest, who was called Caiphas: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.4"><v id="4"></v>And they consulted together, that by subtilty they might apprehend Jesus, and put him to death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.5"><v id="5"></v>But they said: Not on the festival day, lest perhaps there should be a tumult among the people. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.6"><v id="6"></v>And when Jesus was in Bethania, in the house of Simon the leper, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.7"><v id="7"></v>There came to him a woman having an alabaster box of precious ointment, and poured it on his head as he was at table. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.8"><v id="8"></v>And the disciples seeing it, had indignation, saying: To what purpose is this waste? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.9"><v id="9"></v>For this might have been sold for much, and given to the poor. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.10"><v id="10"></v>And Jesus knowing it, said to them: Why do you trouble this woman? for she hath wrought a good work upon me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.11"><v id="11"></v>For the poor you have always with you: but me you have not always. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.12"><v id="12"></v>For she in pouring this ointment upon my body, hath done it for my burial. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.13"><v id="13"></v>Amen I say to you, wheresoever this gospel shall be preached in the whole world, that also which she hath done, shall be told for a memory of her. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.14"><v id="14"></v>Then went one of the twelve, who was called Judas Iscariot, to the chief priests, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.15"><v id="15"></v>And said to them: What will you give me, and I will deliver him unto you? But they appointed him thirty pieces of silver. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.16"><v id="16"></v>And from thenceforth he sought opportunity to betray him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.17"><v id="17"></v>And on the first day of the Azymes, the disciples came to Jesus, saying: Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the pasch? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.18"><v id="18"></v>But Jesus said: Go ye into the city to a certain man, and say to him: the master saith, My time is near at hand, with thee I make the pasch with my disciples. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.19"><v id="19"></v>And the disciples did as Jesus appointed to them, and they prepared the pasch. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.20"><v id="20"></v>But when it was evening, he sat down with his twelve disciples. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.21"><v id="21"></v>And whilst they were eating, he said: Amen I say to you, that one of you is about to betray me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.22"><v id="22"></v>And they being very much troubled, began every one to say: Is it I, Lord? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.23"><v id="23"></v>But he answering, said: He that dippeth his hand with me in the dish, he shall betray me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.24"><v id="24"></v>The Son of man indeed goeth, as it is written of him: but woe to that man by whom the Son of man shall be betrayed: it were better for him, if that man had not been born. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.25"><v id="25"></v>And Judas that betrayed him, answering, said: Is it I, Rabbi? He saith to him: Thou hast said it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.26"><v id="26"></v>And whilst they were at supper, Jesus took bread, and blessed, and broke: and gave to his disciples, and said: Take ye, and eat. This is my body. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.27"><v id="27"></v>And taking the chalice, he gave thanks, and gave to them, saying: Drink ye all of this. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.28"><v id="28"></v>For this is my blood of the new testament, which shall be shed for many unto remission of sins. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.29"><v id="29"></v>And I say to you, I will not drink from henceforth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I shall drink it with you new in the kingdom of my Father. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.30"><v id="30"></v>And a hymn being said, they went out unto mount Olivet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.31"><v id="31"></v>Then Jesus said to them: All you shall be scandalized in me this night. For it is written: I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock shall be dispersed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.32"><v id="32"></v>But after I shall be risen again, I will go before you into Galilee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.33"><v id="33"></v>And Peter answering, said to him: Although all shall be scandalized in thee, I will never be scandalized. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.34"><v id="34"></v>Jesus said to him: Amen I say to thee, that in this night before the cock crow, thou wilt deny me thrice. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.35"><v id="35"></v>Peter saith to him: Yea, though I should die with thee, I will not deny thee. And in like manner said all the disciples. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.36"><v id="36"></v>Then Jesus came with them into a country place which is called Gethsemani; and he said to his disciples: Sit you here, till I go yonder and pray. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.37"><v id="37"></v>And taking with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, he began to grow sorrowful and to be sad. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.38"><v id="38"></v>Then he saith to them: My soul is sorrowful even unto death: stay you here, and watch with me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.39"><v id="39"></v>And going a little further, he fell upon his face, praying, and saying: My Father, if it be possible, let this chalice pass from me. Nevertheless not as I will, but as thou wilt. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.40"><v id="40"></v>And he cometh to his disciples, and findeth them asleep, and he saith to Peter: What? Could you not watch one hour with me? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.41"><v id="41"></v>Watch ye, and pray that ye enter not into temptation. The spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh weak. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.42"><v id="42"></v>Again the second time, he went and prayed, saying: My Father, if this chalice may not pass away, but I must drink it, thy will be done. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.43"><v id="43"></v>And he cometh again and findeth them sleeping: for their eyes were heavy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.44"><v id="44"></v>And leaving them, he went again: and he prayed the third time, saying the selfsame word. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.45"><v id="45"></v>Then he cometh to his disciples, and saith to them: Sleep ye now and take your rest; behold the hour is at hand, and the Son of man shall be betrayed into the hands of sinners. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.46"><v id="46"></v>Rise, let us go: behold he is at hand that will betray me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.47"><v id="47"></v>As he yet spoke, behold Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great multitude with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests and the ancients of the people. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.48"><v id="48"></v>And he that betrayed him, gave them a sign, saying: Whomsoever I shall kiss, that is he, hold him fast. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.49"><v id="49"></v>And forthwith coming to Jesus, he said: Hail, Rabbi. And he kissed him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.50"><v id="50"></v>And Jesus said to him: Friend, whereto art thou come? Then they came up, and laid hands on Jesus, and held him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.51"><v id="51"></v>And behold one of them that were with Jesus, stretching forth his hand, drew out his sword: and striking the servant of the high priest, cut off his ear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.52"><v id="52"></v>Then Jesus saith to him: Put up again thy sword into its place: for all that take the sword shall perish with the sword. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.53"><v id="53"></v>Thinkest thou that I cannot ask my Father, and he will give me presently more than twelve legions of angels? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.54"><v id="54"></v>How then shall the scriptures be fulfilled, that so it must be done? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.55"><v id="55"></v>In that same hour Jesus said to the multitudes: You are come out as it were to a robber with swords and clubs to apprehend me. I sat daily with you, teaching in the temple, and you laid not hands on me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.56"><v id="56"></v>Now all this was done, that the scriptures of the prophets might be fulfilled. Then the disciples all leaving him, fled. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.57"><v id="57"></v>But they holding Jesus led him to Caiphas the high priest, where the scribes and the ancients were assembled. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.58"><v id="58"></v>And Peter followed him afar off, even to the court of the high priest. And going in, he sat with the servants, that he might see the end. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.59"><v id="59"></v>And the chief priests and the whole council sought false witness against Jesus, that they might put him to death: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.60"><v id="60"></v>And they found not, whereas many false witnesses had come in. And last of all there came two false witnesses: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.61"><v id="61"></v>And they said: This man said, I am able to destroy the temple of God, and after three days to rebuild it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.62"><v id="62"></v>And the high priest rising up, said to him: Answerest thou nothing to the things which these witness against thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.63"><v id="63"></v>But Jesus held his peace. And the high priest said to him: I adjure thee by the living God, that thou tell us if thou be the Christ the Son of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.64"><v id="64"></v>Jesus saith to him: Thou hast said it. Nevertheless I say to you, hereafter you shall see the Son of man sitting on the right hand of the power of God, and coming in the clouds of heaven. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.65"><v id="65"></v>Then the high priests rent his garments, saying: He hath blasphemed; what further need have we of witnesses? Behold, now you have heard the blasphemy: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.66"><v id="66"></v>What think you? But they answering, said: He is guilty of death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.67"><v id="67"></v>Then did they spit in his face, and buffeted him: and others struck his face with the palms of their hands, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.68"><v id="68"></v>Saying: Prophesy unto us, O Christ, who is he that struck thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.69"><v id="69"></v>But Peter sat without in the court: and there came to him a servant maid, saying: Thou also wast with Jesus the Galilean. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.70"><v id="70"></v>But he denied before them all, saying: I know not what thou sayest. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.71"><v id="71"></v>And as he went out of the gate, another maid saw him, and she saith to them that were there: This man also was with Jesus of Nazareth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.72"><v id="72"></v>And again he denied with an oath, I know not the man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.73"><v id="73"></v>And after a little while they came that stood by, and said to Peter: Surely thou also art one of them; for even thy speech doth discover thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.74"><v id="74"></v>Then he began to curse and to swear that he knew not the man. And immediately the cock crew. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.26.75"><v id="75"></v>And Peter remembered the word of Jesus which he had said: Before the cock crow, thou wilt deny me thrice. And going forth, he wept bitterly. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.27.0-40.27.0">
<bcv bcv="40.27.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="27"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.1"><v id="1"></v>AND when morning was come, all the chief priests and ancients of the people took counsel against Jesus, that they might put him to death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.2"><v id="2"></v>And they brought him bound, and delivered him to Pontius Pilate the governor. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.3"><v id="3"></v>Then Judas, who betrayed him, seeing that he was condemned, repenting himself, brought back the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and ancients, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.4"><v id="4"></v>Saying: I have sinned in betraying innocent blood. But they said: What is that to us? look thou to it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.5"><v id="5"></v>And casting down the pieces of silver in the temple, he departed: and went and hanged himself with an halter. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.6"><v id="6"></v>But the chief priests having taken the pieces of silver, said: It is not lawful to put them into the corbona, because it is the price of blood. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.7"><v id="7"></v>And after they had consulted together, they bought with them the potter's field, to be a burying place for strangers. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.8"><v id="8"></v>For this cause the field was called Haceldama, that is, The field of blood, even to this day. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.9"><v id="9"></v>Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremias the prophet, saying: And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him that was prized, whom they prized of the children of Israel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.10"><v id="10"></v>And they gave them unto the potter's field, as the Lord appointed to me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.11"><v id="11"></v>And Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor asked him, saying: Art thou the king of the Jews? Jesus saith to him: Thou sayest it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.12"><v id="12"></v>And when he was accused by the chief priests and ancients, he answered nothing. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.13"><v id="13"></v>Then Pilate saith to him: Dost not thou hear how great testimonies they allege against thee? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.14"><v id="14"></v>And he answered him to never a word; so that the governor wondered exceedingly. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.15"><v id="15"></v>Now upon the solemn day the governor was accustomed to release to the people one prisoner, whom they would. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.16"><v id="16"></v>And he had then a notorious prisoner, that was called Barabbas. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.17"><v id="17"></v>They therefore being gathered together, Pilate said: Whom will you that I release to you, Barabbas, or Jesus that is called Christ? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.18"><v id="18"></v>For he knew that for envy they had delivered him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.19"><v id="19"></v>And as he was sitting in the place of judgment, his wife sent to him, saying: Have thou nothing to do with that just man; for I have suffered many things this day in a dream because of him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.20"><v id="20"></v>But the chief priests and ancients persuaded the people, that they should ask Barabbas, and make Jesus away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.21"><v id="21"></v>And the governor answering, said to them: Whether will you of the two to be released unto you? But they said, Barabbas. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.22"><v id="22"></v>Pilate saith to them: What shall I do then with Jesus that is called Christ? They say all: Let him be crucified. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.23"><v id="23"></v>The governor said to them: Why, what evil hath he done? But they cried out the more, saying: Let him be crucified. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.24"><v id="24"></v>And Pilate seeing that he prevailed nothing, but that rather a tumult was made; taking water washed his hands before the people, saying: I am innocent of the blood of this just man; look you to it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.25"><v id="25"></v>And the whole people answering, said: His blood be upon us and our children. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.26"><v id="26"></v>Then he released to them Barabbas, and having scourged Jesus, delivered him unto them to be crucified. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.27"><v id="27"></v>Then the soldiers of the governor taking Jesus into the hall, gathered together unto him the whole band; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.28"><v id="28"></v>And stripping him, they put a scarlet cloak about him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.29"><v id="29"></v>And platting a crown of thorns, they put it upon his head, and a reed in his right hand. And bowing the knee before him, they mocked him, saying: Hail, king of the Jews. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.30"><v id="30"></v>And spitting upon him, they took the reed, and struck his head. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.31"><v id="31"></v>And after they had mocked him, they took off the cloak from him, and put on him his own garments, and led him away to crucify him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.32"><v id="32"></v>And going out, they found a man of Cyrene, named Simon: him they forced to take up his cross. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.33"><v id="33"></v>And they came to the place that is called Golgotha, which is the place of Calvary. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.34"><v id="34"></v>And they gave him wine to drink mingled with gall. And when he had tasted, he would not drink. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.35"><v id="35"></v>And after they had crucified him, they divided his garments, casting lots; that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying: They divided my garments among them; and upon my vesture they cast lots. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.36"><v id="36"></v>And they sat and watched him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.37"><v id="37"></v>And they put over his head his cause written: THIS IS JESUS THE KING OF THE JEWS. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.38"><v id="38"></v>Then were crucified with him two thieves: one on the right hand, and one on the left. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.39"><v id="39"></v>And they that passed by, blasphemed him, wagging their heads, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.40"><v id="40"></v>And saying: Vah, thou that destroyest the temple of God, and in three days dost rebuild it: save thy own self: if thou be the Son of God, come down from the cross. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.41"><v id="41"></v>In like manner also the chief priests, with the scribes and ancients, mocking, said: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.42"><v id="42"></v>He saved others; himself he cannot save. If he be the king of Israel, let him now come down from the cross, and we will believe him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.43"><v id="43"></v>He trusted in God; let him now deliver him if he will have him; for he said: I am the Son of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.44"><v id="44"></v>And the selfsame thing the thieves also, that were crucified with him, reproached him with. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.45"><v id="45"></v>Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over the whole earth, until the ninth hour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.46"><v id="46"></v>And about the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying: Eli, Eli, lamma sabacthani? that is, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.47"><v id="47"></v>And some that stood there and heard, said: This man calleth Elias. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.48"><v id="48"></v>And immediately one of them running took a sponge, and filled it with vinegar; and put it on a reed, and gave him to drink. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.49"><v id="49"></v>And the others said: Let be, let us see whether Elias will come to deliver him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.50"><v id="50"></v>And Jesus again crying with a loud voice, yielded up the ghost. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.51"><v id="51"></v>And behold the veil of the temple was rent in two from the top even to the bottom, and the earth quaked, and the rocks were rent. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.52"><v id="52"></v>And the graves were opened: and many bodies of the saints that had slept arose, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.53"><v id="53"></v>And coming out of the tombs after his resurrection, came into the holy city, and appeared to many. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.54"><v id="54"></v>Now the centurion and they that were with him watching Jesus, having seen the earthquake, and the things that were done, were sore afraid, saying: Indeed this was the Son of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.55"><v id="55"></v>And there were there many women afar off, who had followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering unto him: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.56"><v id="56"></v>Among whom was Mary Magdalen, and Mary the mother of James and Joseph, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.57"><v id="57"></v>And when it was evening, there came a certain rich man of Arimathea, named Joseph, who also himself was a disciple of Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.58"><v id="58"></v>He went to Pilate, and asked the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded that the body should be delivered. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.59"><v id="59"></v>And Joseph taking the body, wrapped it up in a clean linen cloth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.60"><v id="60"></v>And laid it in his own new monument, which he had hewed out in a rock. And he rolled a great stone to the door of the monument, and went his way. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.61"><v id="61"></v>And there was there Mary Magdalen, and the other Mary sitting over against the sepulchre. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.62"><v id="62"></v>And the next day, which followed the day of preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees came together to Pilate, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.63"><v id="63"></v>Saying: Sir, we have remembered, that that seducer said, while he was yet alive: After three days I will rise again. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.64"><v id="64"></v>Command therefore the sepulchre to be guarded until the third day: lest perhaps his disciples come and steal him away, and say to the people: He is risen from the dead; and the last error shall be worse than the first. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.65"><v id="65"></v>Pilate saith to them: You have a guard; go, guard it as you know. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.27.66"><v id="66"></v>And they departing, made the sepulchre sure, sealing the stone, and setting guards. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="40.28.0-40.28.0">
<bcv bcv="40.28.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="28"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.1"><v id="1"></v>AND in the end of the sabbath, when it began to dawn towards the first day of the week, came Mary Magdalen and the other Mary, to see the sepulchre. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.2"><v id="2"></v>And behold there was a great earthquake. For an angel of the Lord descended from heaven, and coming, rolled back the stone, and sat upon it. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.3"><v id="3"></v>And his countenance was as lightning, and his raiment as snow. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.4"><v id="4"></v>And for fear of him, the guards were struck with terror, and became as dead men. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.5"><v id="5"></v>And the angel answering, said to the women: Fear not you; for I know that you seek Jesus who was crucified. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.6"><v id="6"></v>He is not here, for he is risen, as he said. Come, and see the place where the Lord was laid. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.7"><v id="7"></v>And going quickly, tell ye his disciples that he is risen: and behold he will go before you into Galilee; there you shall see him. Lo, I have foretold it to you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.8"><v id="8"></v>And they went out quickly from the sepulchre with fear and great joy, running to tell his disciples. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.9"><v id="9"></v>And behold Jesus met them, saying: All hail. But they came up and took hold of his feet, and adored him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.10"><v id="10"></v>Then Jesus said to them: Fear not. Go, tell my brethren that they go into Galilee, there they shall see me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.11"><v id="11"></v>Who when they were departed, behold some of the guards came into the city, and told the chief priests all things that had been done. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.12"><v id="12"></v>And they being assembled together with the ancients, taking counsel, gave a great sum of money to the soldiers, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.13"><v id="13"></v>Saying: Say you, His disciples came by night, and stole him away when we were asleep. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.14"><v id="14"></v>And if the governor shall hear this, we will persuade him, and secure you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.15"><v id="15"></v>So they taking the money, did as they were taught: and this word was spread abroad among the Jews even unto this day. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.16"><v id="16"></v>And the eleven disciples went into Galilee, unto the mountain where Jesus had appointed them. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.17"><v id="17"></v>And seeing them they adored: but some doubted. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.18"><v id="18"></v>And Jesus coming, spoke to them, saying: All power is given to me in heaven and in earth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.19"><v id="19"></v>Going therefore, teach ye all nations; baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="40.28.20"><v id="20"></v>Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you: and behold I am with you all days, even to the consummation of the world.</bcv></p0>
</container>
</container>

</bk>
