<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="usfx_to_xhtml.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">


<bk id="64" name="3 JOHN" short_name="3JO" order="71">
<mbk>64</mbk>

<container id="64.1.0-64.1.0">
<bcv bcv="64.1.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="1"></ch></bcv>

<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.1"><v id="1"></v>The ancient to the dearly beloved Gaius, whom I love in truth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.2"><v id="2"></v>Dearly beloved, concerning all things I make it my prayer that thou mayest proceed prosperously, and fare well as thy soul doth prosperously. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.3"><v id="3"></v>I was exceedingly glad when the brethren came and gave testimony to the truth in thee, even as thou walkest in the truth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.4"><v id="4"></v>I have no greater grace than this, to hear that my children walk in truth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.5"><v id="5"></v>Dearly beloved, thou dost faithfully whatever thou dost for the brethren, and that for strangers, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.6"><v id="6"></v>Who have given testimony to thy charity in the sight of the church: whom thou shalt do well to bring forward on their way in a manner worthy of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.7"><v id="7"></v>Because, for his name they went out, taking nothing of the Gentiles. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.8"><v id="8"></v>We therefore ought to receive such, that we may be fellow helpers of the truth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.9"><v id="9"></v>I had written perhaps to the church: but Diotrephes, who loveth to have the pre-eminence among them, doth not receive us. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.10"><v id="10"></v>For this cause, if I come, I will advertise his works which he doth, with malicious words prating against us. And as if these things were not enough for him, neither doth he himself receive the brethren, and them that do receive them he forbiddeth, and casteth out of the church. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.11"><v id="11"></v>Dearly beloved, follow not that which is evil, but that which is good. He that doth good, is of God: he that doth evil, hath not seen God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.12"><v id="12"></v>To Demetrius testimony is given by all, and by the truth itself, yea and we also give testimony: and thou knowest that our testimony is true. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.13"><v id="13"></v>I had many things to write unto thee: but I would not by ink and pen write to thee. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="64.1.14"><v id="14"></v>But I hope speedily to see thee, and we will speak mouth to mouth. Peace be to thee. Our friends salute thee. Salute the friends by name.</bcv></p0>
</container>
</container>

</bk>
