<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="usfx_to_xhtml.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">


<bk id="50" name="PHILIPPIANS" short_name="PHP" order="57">
<mbk>50</mbk>

<container id="50.1.0-50.1.0">
<bcv bcv="50.1.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="1"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.1"><v id="1"></v>Paul and Timothy, the servants of Jesus Christ; to all the saints in Christ Jesus, who are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.2"><v id="2"></v>Grace be unto you, and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.3"><v id="3"></v>I give thanks to my God in every remembrance of you, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.4"><v id="4"></v>Always in all my prayers making supplication for you all, with joy; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.5"><v id="5"></v>For your communication in the gospel of Christ from the first day until now. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.6"><v id="6"></v>Being confident of this very thing, that he, who hath begun a good work in you, will perfect it unto the day of Christ Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.7"><v id="7"></v>As it is meet for me to think this for you all, for that I have you in my heart; and that in my bands, and in the defence and confirmation of the gospel, you all are partakers of my joy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.8"><v id="8"></v>For God is my witness, how I long after you all in the bowels of Jesus Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.9"><v id="9"></v>And this I pray, that your charity may more and more abound in knowledge, and in all understanding: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.10"><v id="10"></v>That you may approve the better things, that you may be sincere and without offence unto the day of Christ, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.11"><v id="11"></v>Filled with the fruit of justice, through Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.12"><v id="12"></v>Now, brethren, I desire you should know, that the things which have happened to me, have fallen out rather to the furtherance of the gospel: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.13"><v id="13"></v>So that my bands are made manifest in Christ, in all the court, and in all other places; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.14"><v id="14"></v>And many of the brethren in the Lord, growing confident by my bands, are much more bold to speak the word of God without fear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.15"><v id="15"></v>Some indeed, even out of envy and contention; but some also for good will preach Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.16"><v id="16"></v>Some out of charity, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.17"><v id="17"></v>And some out of contention preach Christ not sincerely: supposing that they raise affliction to my bands. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.18"><v id="18"></v>But what then? So that by all means, whether by occasion, or by truth, Christ be preached: in this also I rejoice, yea, and will rejoice. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.19"><v id="19"></v>For I know that this shall fall out to me unto salvation, through your prayer, and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.20"><v id="20"></v>According to my expectation and hope; that in nothing I shall be confounded, but with all confidence, as always, so now also shall Christ be magnified in my body, wither it be by life, or by death. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.21"><v id="21"></v>For to me, to live is Christ; and to die is gain. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.22"><v id="22"></v>And if to live in the flesh, that is to me the fruit of labour, and what I shall choose I know not. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.23"><v id="23"></v>But I am straitened between two: having a desire to be dissolved and to be with Christ, a thing by far the better. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.24"><v id="24"></v>But to abide still in the flesh, is needful for you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.25"><v id="25"></v>And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide, and continue with you all, for your furtherance and joy of faith: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.26"><v id="26"></v>That your rejoicing may abound in Christ Jesus for me, by my coming to you again. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.27"><v id="27"></v>Only let your conversation be worthy of the gospel of Christ: that, whether I come and see you, or, being absent, may hear of you, that you stand fast in one spirit, with one mind labouring together for the faith of the gospel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.28"><v id="28"></v>And in nothing be ye terrified by the adversaries: which to them is a cause of perdition, but to you of salvation, and this from God: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.29"><v id="29"></v>For unto you it is given for Christ, not only to believe in him, but also to suffer for him. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.1.30"><v id="30"></v>Having the same conflict as that which you have seen in me, and now have heard of me. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="50.2.0-50.2.0">
<bcv bcv="50.2.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="2"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.1"><v id="1"></v>If there be therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of charity, if any society of the spirit, if any bowels of commiseration: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.2"><v id="2"></v>Fulfil ye my joy, that you may be of one mind, having the same charity, being of one accord, agreeing in sentiment. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.3"><v id="3"></v>Let nothing be done through contention, neither by vain glory: but in humility, let each esteem others better than themselves: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.4"><v id="4"></v>Each one not considering the things that are his own, but those that are other men's. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.5"><v id="5"></v>For let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.6"><v id="6"></v>Who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.7"><v id="7"></v>But emptied himself, taking the form of a servant, being made in the likeness of men, and in habit found as a man. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.8"><v id="8"></v>He humbled himself, becoming obedient unto death, even to the death of the cross. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.9"><v id="9"></v>For which cause God also hath exalted him, and hath given him a name which is above all names: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.10"><v id="10"></v>That in the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of those that are in heaven, on earth, and under the earth: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.11"><v id="11"></v>And that every tongue should confess that the Lord Jesus Christ is in the glory of God the Father. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.12"><v id="12"></v>Wherefore, my dearly beloved, (as you have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but much more now in my absence,) with fear and trembling work out your salvation. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.13"><v id="13"></v>For it is God who worketh in you, both to will and to accomplish, according to his good will. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.14"><v id="14"></v>And do ye all things without murmurings and hesitations; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.15"><v id="15"></v>That you may be blameless, and sincere children of God, without reproof, in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation; among whom you shine as lights in the world. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.16"><v id="16"></v>Holding forth the word of life to my glory in the day of Christ, because I have not run in vain, nor laboured in vain. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.17"><v id="17"></v>Yea, and if I be made a victim upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I rejoice, and congratulate with you all. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.18"><v id="18"></v>And for the selfsame thing do you also rejoice, and congratulate with me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.19"><v id="19"></v>And I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy unto you shortly, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know the things concerning you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.20"><v id="20"></v>For I have no man so of the same mind, who with sincere affection is solicitous for you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.21"><v id="21"></v>For all seek the things that are their own; not the things that are Jesus Christ's. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.22"><v id="22"></v>Now know ye the proof of him, that as a son with the father, so hath he served with me in the gospel. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.23"><v id="23"></v>Him therefore I hope to send unto you immediately, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.24"><v id="24"></v>And I trust in the Lord, that I myself also shall come to you shortly. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.25"><v id="25"></v>But I have thought it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow labourer, and fellow soldier, but your apostle, and he that hath ministered to my wants. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.26"><v id="26"></v>For indeed he longed after you all: and was sad, for that you had heard that he was sick. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.27"><v id="27"></v>For indeed he was sick, nigh unto death; but God had mercy on him; and not only on him, but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.28"><v id="28"></v>Therefore I sent him the more speedily: that seeing him again, you may rejoice, and I may be without sorrow. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.29"><v id="29"></v>Receive him therefore with all joy in the Lord; and treat with honour such as he is. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.2.30"><v id="30"></v>Because for the work of Christ he came to the point of death: delivering his life, that he might fulfil that which on your part was wanting towards my service. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="50.3.0-50.3.0">
<bcv bcv="50.3.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="3"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.1"><v id="1"></v>As to the rest, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not wearisome, but to you it is necessary. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.2"><v id="2"></v>Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the concision. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.3"><v id="3"></v>For we are the circumcision, who in spirit serve God; and glory in Christ Jesus, not having confidence in the flesh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.4"><v id="4"></v>Though I might also have confidence in the flesh. If any other thinketh he may have confidence in the flesh, I more, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.5"><v id="5"></v>Being circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrews; according to the law, a Pharisee: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.6"><v id="6"></v>According to zeal, persecuting the church of God; according to the justice that is in the law, conversing without blame. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.7"><v id="7"></v>But the things that were gain to me, the same I have counted loss for Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.8"><v id="8"></v>Furthermore I count all things to be but loss for the excellent knowledge of Jesus Christ my Lord; for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and count them but as dung, that I may gain Christ: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.9"><v id="9"></v>And may be found in him, not having my justice, which is of the law, but that which is of the faith of Christ Jesus, which is of God, justice in faith: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.10"><v id="10"></v>That I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being made conformable to his death, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.11"><v id="11"></v>If by any means I may attain to the resurrection which is from the dead. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.12"><v id="12"></v>Not as though I has already attained, or were already perfect; but I follow after, if I may by any means apprehend, wherein I am also apprehended by Christ Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.13"><v id="13"></v>Brethren, I do not count myself to have apprehended. But one thing I do: forgetting the things that are behind, and stretching forth myself to those that are before, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.14"><v id="14"></v>I press towards the mark, to the prize of the supernal vocation of God in Christ Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.15"><v id="15"></v>Let us therefore, as many as are perfect, be thus minded; and if in any thing you be otherwise minded, this also God will reveal to you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.16"><v id="16"></v>Nevertheless whereunto we are come, that we be of the same mind, let us also continue in the same rule. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.17"><v id="17"></v>Be ye followers of me, brethren, and observe them who walk so as you have our model. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.18"><v id="18"></v>For many walk, of whom I have told you often (and now tell you weeping), that they are enemies of the cross of Christ; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.19"><v id="19"></v>Whose end is destruction; whose God is their belly; and whose glory is in their shame; who mind earthly things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.20"><v id="20"></v>But our conversation is in heaven; from whence also we look for the Saviour, our Lord Jesus Christ, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.3.21"><v id="21"></v>Who will reform the body of our lowness, made like to the body of his glory, according to the operation whereby also he is able to subdue all things unto himself. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="50.4.0-50.4.0">
<bcv bcv="50.4.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="4"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.1"><v id="1"></v>Therefore, my dearly beloved brethren, and most desired, my joy and my crown; so stand fast in the Lord, my dearly beloved. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.2"><v id="2"></v>I beg of Evodia, and I beseech Syntyche, to be of one mind in the Lord. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.3"><v id="3"></v>And I entreat thee also, my sincere companion, help those women who have laboured with me in the gospel, with Clement and the rest of my fellow labourers, whose names are in the book of life. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.4"><v id="4"></v>Rejoice in the Lord always; again, I say, rejoice. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.5"><v id="5"></v>Let your modesty be known to all men. The Lord is nigh. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.6"><v id="6"></v>Be nothing solicitous; but in every thing, by prayer and supplication, with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.7"><v id="7"></v>And the peace of God, which surpasseth all understanding, keep your hearts and minds in Christ Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.8"><v id="8"></v>For the rest, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever modest, whatsoever just, whatsoever holy, whatsoever lovely, whatsoever of good fame, if there be any virtue, if any praise of discipline, think on these things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.9"><v id="9"></v>The things which you have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, these do ye, and the God of peace shall be with you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.10"><v id="10"></v>Now I rejoice in the Lord exceedingly, that now at length your thought for me hath flourished again, as you did also think; but you were busied. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.11"><v id="11"></v>I speak not as it were for want. For I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, to be content therewith. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.12"><v id="12"></v>I know both how to be brought low, and I know how to abound: (everywhere, and in all things I am instructed) both to be full, and to be hungry; both to abound, and to suffer need. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.13"><v id="13"></v>I can do all these things in him who strengtheneth me. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.14"><v id="14"></v>Nevertheless you have done well in communicating to my tribulation. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.15"><v id="15"></v>And you also know, O Philippians, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving, but you only: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.16"><v id="16"></v>For unto Thessalonica also you sent once and again for my use. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.17"><v id="17"></v>Not that I seek the gift, but I seek the fruit that may abound to your account. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.18"><v id="18"></v>But I have all, and abound: I am filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things you sent, an odour of sweetness, an acceptable sacrifice, pleasing to God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.19"><v id="19"></v>And may my God supply all your want, according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.20"><v id="20"></v>Now to God and our Father be glory world without end. Amen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.21"><v id="21"></v>Salute ye every saint in Christ Jesus. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.22"><v id="22"></v>The brethren who are with me, salute you. All the saints salute you; especially they that are of Caesar's household. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="50.4.23"><v id="23"></v>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</bcv></p0>
</container>
</container>

</bk>
