<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="usfx_to_xhtml.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">


<bk id="63" name="2 JOHN" short_name="2JO" order="70">
<mbk>63</mbk>

<container id="63.1.0-63.1.0">
<bcv bcv="63.1.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="1"></ch></bcv>

<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.1"><v id="1"></v>The ancient to the lady Elect, and her children, whom I love in the truth, and not I only, but also all they that have known the truth, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.2"><v id="2"></v>For the sake of the truth which dwelleth in us, and shall be with us for ever. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.3"><v id="3"></v>Grace be with you, mercy, and peace from God the Father, and from Christ Jesus the Son of the Father; in truth and charity. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.4"><v id="4"></v>I was exceeding glad, that I found of thy children walking in truth, as we have received a commandment from the Father. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.5"><v id="5"></v>And now I beseech thee, lady, not as writing a new commandment to thee, but that which we have had from the beginning, that we love one another. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.6"><v id="6"></v>And this is charity, that we walk according to his commandments. For this is the commandment, that, as you have heard from the beginning, you should walk in the same: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.7"><v id="7"></v>For many seducers are gone out into the world, who confess not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh: this is a seducer and an antichrist. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.8"><v id="8"></v>Look to yourselves, that you lose not the things which you have wrought: but that you may receive a full reward. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.9"><v id="9"></v>Whosoever revolteth, and continueth not in the doctrine of Christ, hath not God. He that continueth in the doctrine, the same hath both the Father and the Son. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.10"><v id="10"></v>If any man come to you, and bring not this doctrine, receive him not into the house nor say to him, God speed you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.11"><v id="11"></v>For he that saith unto him, God speed you, communicateth with his wicked works. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.12"><v id="12"></v>Having more things to write unto you, I would not by paper and ink: for I hope that I shall be with you, and speak face to face: that your joy may be full. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="63.1.13"><v id="13"></v>The children of thy sister Elect salute thee.</bcv></p0>
</container>
</container>

</bk>
