<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="usfx_to_xhtml.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">


<bk id="60" name="1 PETER" short_name="1PE" order="67">
<mbk>60</mbk>

<container id="60.1.0-60.1.0">
<bcv bcv="60.1.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="1"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.1"><v id="1"></v>Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the strangers dispersed through Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia, elect, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.2"><v id="2"></v>According to the foreknowledge of God the Father, unto the sanctification of the Spirit, unto obedience and sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: Grace unto you and peace be multiplied. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.3"><v id="3"></v>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his great mercy hath regenerated us unto a lively hope, by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.4"><v id="4"></v>Unto an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled, and that can not fade, reserved in heaven for you, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.5"><v id="5"></v>Who, by the power of God, are kept by faith unto salvation, ready to be revealed in the last time. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.6"><v id="6"></v>Wherein you shall greatly rejoice, if now you must be for a little time made sorrowful in divers temptations: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.7"><v id="7"></v>That the trial of your faith (much more precious than gold which is tried by the fire) may be found unto praise and glory and honour at the appearing of Jesus Christ: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.8"><v id="8"></v>Whom having not seen, you love: in whom also now, though you see him not, you believe: and believing shall rejoice with joy unspeakable and glorified; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.9"><v id="9"></v>Receiving the end of your faith, even the salvation of your souls. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.10"><v id="10"></v>Of which salvation the prophets have inquired and diligently searched, who prophesied of the grace to come in you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.11"><v id="11"></v>Searching what or what manner of time the Spirit of Christ in them did signify: when it foretold those sufferings that are in Christ, and the glories that should follow: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.12"><v id="12"></v>To whom it was revealed, that not to themselves, but to you they ministered those things which are now declared to you by them that have preached the gospel to you, the Holy Ghost being sent down from heaven, on whom the angels desire to look. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.13"><v id="13"></v>Wherefore having the loins of your mind girt up, being sober, trust perfectly in the grace which is offered you in the revelation of Jesus Christ, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.14"><v id="14"></v>As children of obedience, not fashioned according to the former desires of your ignorance: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.15"><v id="15"></v>But according to him that hath called you, who is holy, be you also in all manner of conversation holy: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.16"><v id="16"></v>Because it is written: You shall be holy, for I am holy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.17"><v id="17"></v>And if you invoke as Father him who, without respect of persons, judgeth according to every one's work: converse in fear during the time of your sojourning here. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.18"><v id="18"></v>Knowing that you were not redeemed with corruptible things as gold or silver, from your vain conversation of the tradition of your fathers: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.19"><v id="19"></v>But with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb unspotted and undefiled, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.20"><v id="20"></v>Foreknown indeed before the foundation of the world, but manifested in the last times for you, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.21"><v id="21"></v>Who through him are faithful in God, who raised him up from the dead, and hath given him glory, that your faith and hope might be in God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.22"><v id="22"></v>Purifying your souls in the obedience of charity, with a brotherly love, from a sincere heart love one another earnestly: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.23"><v id="23"></v>Being born again not of corruptible seed, but incorruptible, by the word of God who liveth and remaineth for ever. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.24"><v id="24"></v>For all flesh is as grass; and all the glory thereof as the flower of grass. The grass is withered, and the flower thereof is fallen away. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.1.25"><v id="25"></v>But the word of the Lord endureth for ever. And this is the word which by the gospel hath been preached unto you. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="60.2.0-60.2.0">
<bcv bcv="60.2.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="2"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.1"><v id="1"></v>Wherefore laying away all malice, and all guile, and dissimulations, and envies, and all detractions, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.2"><v id="2"></v>As newborn babes, desire the rational milk without guile, that thereby you may grow unto salvation: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.3"><v id="3"></v>If so be you have tasted that the Lord is sweet. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.4"><v id="4"></v>Unto whom coming, as to a living stone, rejected indeed by men, but chosen and made honourable by God: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.5"><v id="5"></v>Be you also as living stones built up, a spiritual house, a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God by Jesus Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.6"><v id="6"></v>Wherefore it is said in the scripture: Behold, I lay in Sion a chief corner stone, elect, precious. And he that shall believe in him, shall not be confounded. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.7"><v id="7"></v>To you therefore that believe, he is honour: but to them that believe not, the stone which the builders rejected, the same is made the head of the corner: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.8"><v id="8"></v>And a stone of stumbling, and a rock of scandal, to them who stumble at the word, neither do believe, whereunto also they are set. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.9"><v id="9"></v>But you are a chosen generation, a kingly priesthood, a holy nation, a purchased people: that you may declare his virtues, who hath called you out of darkness into his marvellous light: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.10"><v id="10"></v>Who in time past were not a people: but are now the people of God. Who had not obtained mercy; but now have obtained mercy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.11"><v id="11"></v>Dearly beloved, I beseech you as strangers and pilgrims, to refrain yourselves from carnal desires which war against the soul, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.12"><v id="12"></v>Having your conversation good among the Gentiles: that whereas they speak against you as evildoers, they may, by the good works, which they shall behold in you, glorify God in the day of visitation. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.13"><v id="13"></v>Be ye subject therefore to every human creature for God's sake: whether it be to the king as excelling; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.14"><v id="14"></v>Or to governors as sent by him for the punishment of evildoers, and for the praise of the good: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.15"><v id="15"></v>For so is the will of God, that by doing well you may put to silence the ignorance of foolish men: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.16"><v id="16"></v>As free, and not as making liberty a cloak for malice, but as the servants of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.17"><v id="17"></v>Honour all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Honour the king. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.18"><v id="18"></v>Servants, be subject to your masters with all fear, not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.19"><v id="19"></v>For this is thankworthy, if for conscience towards God, a man endure sorrows, suffering wrongfully. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.20"><v id="20"></v>For what glory is it, if committing sin, and being buffeted for it, you endure? But if doing well you suffer patiently; this is thankworthy before God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.21"><v id="21"></v>For unto this are you called: because Christ also suffered for us, leaving you an example that you should follow his steps. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.22"><v id="22"></v>Who did no sin, neither was guile found in his mouth. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.23"><v id="23"></v>Who, when he was reviled, did not revile: when he suffered, he threatened not: but delivered himself to him that judged him unjustly. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.24"><v id="24"></v>Who his own self bore our sins in his body upon the tree: that we, being dead to sins, should live to justice: by whose stripes you were healed. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.2.25"><v id="25"></v>For you were as sheep going astray; but you are now converted to the shepherd and bishop of your souls. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="60.3.0-60.3.0">
<bcv bcv="60.3.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="3"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.1"><v id="1"></v>In like manner also let wives be subject to their husbands: that if any believe not the word, they may be won without the word, by the conversation of the wives. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.2"><v id="2"></v>Considering your chaste conversation with fear. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.3"><v id="3"></v>Whose adorning let it not be the outward plaiting of the hair, or the wearing of gold, or the putting on of apparel: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.4"><v id="4"></v>But the hidden man of the heart in the incorruptibility of a quiet and a meek spirit, which is rich in the sight of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.5"><v id="5"></v>For after this manner heretofore the holy women also, who trusted in God, adorned themselves, being in subjection to their own husbands: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.6"><v id="6"></v>As Sara obeyed Abraham, calling him lord: whose daughters you are, doing well, and not fearing any disturbance. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.7"><v id="7"></v>Ye husbands, likewise dwelling with them according to knowledge, giving honour to the female as to the weaker vessel, and as to the co-heirs of the grace of life: that your prayers be not hindered. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.8"><v id="8"></v>And in fine, be ye all of one mind, having compassion one of another, being lovers of the brotherhood, merciful, modest, humble: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.9"><v id="9"></v>Not rendering evil for evil, nor railing for railing, but contrariwise, blessing: for unto this are you called, that you may inherit a blessing. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.10"><v id="10"></v>For he that will love life, and see good days, let him refrain his tongue from evil, and his lips that they speak no guile. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.11"><v id="11"></v>Let him decline from evil, and do good: let him seek after peace and pursue it: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.12"><v id="12"></v>Because the eyes of the Lord are upon the just, and his ears unto their prayers: but the countenance of the Lord upon them that do evil things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.13"><v id="13"></v>And who is he that can hurt you, if you be zealous of good? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.14"><v id="14"></v>But if also you suffer any thing for justice' sake, blessed are ye. And be not afraid of their fear, and be not troubled. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.15"><v id="15"></v>But sanctify the Lord Christ in your hearts, being ready always to satisfy every one that asketh you a reason of that hope which is in you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.16"><v id="16"></v>But with modesty and fear, having a good conscience: that whereas they speak evil of you, they may be ashamed who falsely accuse your good conversation in Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.17"><v id="17"></v>For it is better doing well (if such be the will of God) to suffer, than doing ill. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.18"><v id="18"></v>Because Christ also died once for our sins, the just for the unjust: that he might offer us to God, being put to death indeed in the flesh, but enlivened in the spirit, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.19"><v id="19"></v>In which also coming he preached to those spirits that were in prison: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.20"><v id="20"></v>Which had been some time incredulous, when they waited for the patience of God in the days of Noe, when the ark was a building: wherein a few, that is, eight souls, were saved by water. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.21"><v id="21"></v>Whereunto baptism being of the like form, now saveth you also: not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the examination of a good conscience towards God by the resurrection of Jesus Christ. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.3.22"><v id="22"></v>Who is on the right hand of God, swallowing down death, that we might be made heirs of life everlasting: being gone into heaven, the angels and powers and virtues being made subject to him. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="60.4.0-60.4.0">
<bcv bcv="60.4.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="4"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.1"><v id="1"></v>Christ therefore having suffered in the flesh, be you also armed with the same thought: for he that hath suffered in the flesh, hath ceased from sins: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.2"><v id="2"></v>That now he may live the rest of his time in the flesh , not after the desires of men, but according to the will of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.3"><v id="3"></v>For the time past is sufficient to have fulfilled the will of the Gentiles, for them who have walked in riotousness, lusts, excess of wine, revellings, banquetings, and unlawful worshipping of idols. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.4"><v id="4"></v>Wherein they think it strange, that you run not with them into the same confusion of riotousness, speaking evil of you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.5"><v id="5"></v>Who shall render account to him, who is ready to judge the living and the dead. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.6"><v id="6"></v>For, for this cause was the gospel preached also to the dead: that they might be judged indeed according to men, in the flesh; but may live according to God, in the Spirit. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.7"><v id="7"></v>But the end of all is at hand. Be prudent therefore, and watch in prayers. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.8"><v id="8"></v>But before all things have a constant mutual charity among yourselves: for charity covereth a multitude of sins. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.9"><v id="9"></v>Using hospitality one towards another, without murmuring, </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.10"><v id="10"></v>As every man hath received grace, ministering the same one to another: as good stewards of the manifold grace of God. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.11"><v id="11"></v>If any man speak, let him speak, as the words of God. If any man minister, let him do it, as of the power, which God administereth: that in all things God may be honoured through Jesus Christ: to whom is glory and empire for ever and ever. Amen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.12"><v id="12"></v>Dearly beloved, think not strange the burning heat which is to try you, as if some new thing happened to you; </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.13"><v id="13"></v>But if you partake of the sufferings of Christ, rejoice that when his glory shall be revealed, you may also be glad with exceeding joy. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.14"><v id="14"></v>If you be reproached for the name of Christ, you shall be blessed: for that which is of the honour, glory, and power of God, and that which is his Spirit, resteth upon you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.15"><v id="15"></v>But let none of you suffer as a murderer, or a thief, or a railer, or a coveter of other men's things. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.16"><v id="16"></v>But if as a Christian, let him not be ashamed, but let him glorify God in that name. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.17"><v id="17"></v>For the time is, that judgment should begin at the house of God. And if first at us, what shall be the end of them that believe not the gospel of God? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.18"><v id="18"></v>And if the just man shall scarcely be saved, where shall the ungodly and the sinner appear? </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.4.19"><v id="19"></v>Wherefore let them also that suffer according to the will of God, commend their souls in good deeds to the faithful Creator. </bcv></p0>

</container>

<container id="60.5.0-60.5.0">
<bcv bcv="60.5.0"><half>&nbsp;</half><ch id="5"></ch></bcv>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.1"><v id="1"></v>The ancients therefore that are among you, I beseech, who am myself also an ancient, and a witness of the sufferings of Christ: as also a partaker of that glory which is to be revealed in time to come: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.2"><v id="2"></v>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking care of it, not by constraint, but willingly, according to God: not for filthy lucre's sake, but voluntarily: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.3"><v id="3"></v>Neither as lording it over the clergy, but being made a pattern of the flock from the heart. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.4"><v id="4"></v>And when the prince of pastors shall appear, you shall receive a never fading crown of glory. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.5"><v id="5"></v>In like manner, ye young men, be subject to the ancients. And do you all insinuate humility one to another, for God resisteth the proud, but to the humble he giveth grace. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.6"><v id="6"></v>Be you humbled therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in the time of visitation: </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.7"><v id="7"></v>Casting all your care upon him, for he hath care of you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.8"><v id="8"></v>Be sober and watch: because your adversary the devil, as a roaring lion, goeth about seeking whom he may devour. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.9"><v id="9"></v>Whom resist ye, strong in faith: knowing that the same affliction befalls your brethren who are in the world. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.10"><v id="10"></v>But the God of all grace, who hath called us into his eternal glory in Christ Jesus, after you have suffered a little, will himself perfect you, and confirm you, and establish you. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.11"><v id="11"></v>To him be glory and empire for ever and ever. Amen. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.12"><v id="12"></v>By Sylvanus, a faithful brother unto you, as I think, I have written briefly: beseeching and testifying that this is the true grace of God, wherein you stand. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.13"><v id="13"></v>The church that is in Babylon, elected together with you, saluteth you: and so doth my son Mark. </bcv></p0>
<p0><bcv bcv="60.5.14"><v id="14"></v>Salute one another with a holy kiss. Grace be to all you, who are in Christ Jesus. Amen.</bcv></p0>
</container>
</container>

</bk>
